<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Love to the life, or, Some meditations upon loving, and washing in the blood of Christ together, with a tast of gospel-promises, as the churches stock, or, believers patrimony. By R.M. the Benjamin of his Fathers house.</title>
            <author>Mayhew, R. (Richard)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 144 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 80 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50394</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1440</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217769</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829415</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829415</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33854</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50394)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33854)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1919:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Love to the life, or, Some meditations upon loving, and washing in the blood of Christ together, with a tast of gospel-promises, as the churches stock, or, believers patrimony. By R.M. the Benjamin of his Fathers house.</title>
                  <author>Mayhew, R. (Richard)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 142, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for B. Harris, at the Stationers Arms in Swithins Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno 1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: Richard Mayhew.</note>
                  <note>With a final leaf of advertisement.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Blood --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Biblical teaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33854:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>LOVE to the LIFE,</hi> Or, ſome MEDITATIONS UPON LOVING, and WASHING In the Blood of Chriſt; TOGETHER, With a Taſt of <hi>Goſpel-Promiſes,</hi> as the CHURCHES STOCK, or, BELIEVERS PATRIMONY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> R. M. <hi>the Benjamin of his Fathers houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>As the Father hath loved me, ſo have I loved you, continue ye in my Love, <bibl>
                  <hi>Jo. 15.9.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>If I waſh thee not, thou haſt no part with me, <bibl>
                  <hi>Jo. 13 8.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>If ye be Chriſts, then are ye Abrahams ſeed, and Heirs, according to the promiſe, <bibl>
                  <hi>Gal. 3.29.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Mala mea, purè mala ſunt, &amp; mea ſunt; Bona au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem mea, nec pure bona ſunt, nec mea ſunt.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>B. Harris,</hi> at the <hi>Stationers</hi> Arms in <hi>Swithins Alley.</hi> Anno 1674.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:33854:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33854:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:33854:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33854:3"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian, and Candid Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THou mayſt wonder to ſee Me (the <hi>Benjamin</hi> of my Fathers Houſe) to add to the Heap, and Pile of Books; If (my wickedly-wicked heart, deceive me not) not Glory (unleſs of God,) nor Gain (unleſs of Souls) have been the wheels on which I have moved, and the grand Incentives to Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife the Babe into the World. A Book may preach when the Author dare not; when the Author can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not; yea (which is more) when the Author is not. I hope I can ſay (without a Flouriſh) that this Babe had been ſtifflled in the womb, and not ſeen the Light, had not my higheſt Ambition (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb facs="tcp:33854:4"/>Brotherly Solicitation) been my Fathers Glory, and my Fellow Creatures Good.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12 12</note> 
               <hi>Though, of making Books, there is no end, and much reading is a wearineſs to the Fleſh;</hi> Yet, there are ſome Books, of which I may ſay, as ſome Phiſicians ſpeak of their Pills, there are <hi>Pilula ſine quibus;</hi> that is, <hi>ſine quibus eſſe nolo,</hi> without which they would not be: 'Tis true, the Bible, is the Book of Books, for that is Gods Book: yet there are ſome <hi>Libelli ſine quibus;</hi> ſome little Books without which I would not be.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> If this little Tract, have been preached to the Ear, and ſhall be pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ented to the Eye, then the ſtrength of <hi>Iſrael</hi> imprint it upon the Heart.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> If thou findeſt not in this Book (Much in a Little) yet wonder not,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 8.9.</note> for <hi>I am but of yeſterday, and know nothing;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:33854:4"/>or <hi>not,</hi> according to the Margent. If any ſay, why do this Dwarf trouble the World, that's under a Glut of Books already? I ſhall modeſtly reply, that, though wordly praiſe, and profit, be the two Lackeys of moſt mens La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, yet (through Grace) I have been hunting after neither.</p>
            <p>The Pen (by far) ſpreads it ſelf farther, then the Voice can reach, the Pen, is an artificial Tongue, and ſheaks to the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, as well as the preſent; yea, it ſpeaks not to the preſent Age only, but to the ſucceeding Ages alſo: The Pen, is a kind of Image of Eternity, and will make a Man live, when He is dead:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>Though the Prophets do not live for ever,</hi> yet their Labours may;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.4.</note> ana <hi>Abel (though dead) yet ſpeaketh;</hi> or, is ſpoken off.</p>
            <p>What <hi>Solon</hi> ſaia concerning Laws (that there were many good
<pb facs="tcp:33854:5"/>Laws made, but there wanted one Law, to make them put all thoſe Laws in Execution;) So, I may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay concerning Books; there are many good Book: writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, but there wanteth one Book, to make us put thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ood Books in practiſe: O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuch a Book were worth writing, and worth read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.
<note place="margin">Auguſtine, with Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſius.</note> I hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> read of one, that was much taken with the Book of anoth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but not finding the name of Chriſt in it, he could not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyally affect it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> I doubt not, but the Name of Chriſt (who hath a Name above every Name) will be Legible in this little little Book, for 'tis a Narrative (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my Stature) of Chriſts <hi>Loving,</hi> and <hi>Waſhing</hi> out of Love.</p>
            <p>I would hope, I ſhall never have cauſe to ſay concerning this Book, as <hi>Nero</hi> did concerning
<pb facs="tcp:33854:5"/>a piece of his, <hi>(ultinum neſciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſem Literas)</hi> wiſhing, it had never been written. God hath two Books, his Works, and his Word; the Book of the Creatures, and the Book of the Scriptures; As for this latter Book (the Holy Scriptures of Truth) they are Chriſts Letters of Credence; that when a poor deſponding, doubting, and drooping Souls can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee Chriſt, it may read of a Christ; and hear of a Chriſt, and ſo hear from a Chriſt. Now, (though, for this Book (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially) we are to ble<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s God for) as there is a different Reading, and what is ſaid of a part, is tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of the whole;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.3.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed is he (or ſhe) that rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth, and they that hear the words of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, and keep thoſe ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, which are written there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in;</hi> Yet, there are many other good Books, for which I can bleſs
<pb facs="tcp:33854:6"/>God eſpecially where there is much of a Chriſt; moſt of a Chriſt, as Saviour, and Soveraign.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> Was not that a ſad day, when the Apoſtles (who were ſo good Preachers) were forbidden preaching?
<note place="margin">Acts <hi>4.17.18.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>They cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them, and commanded them not to ſpeak at all, nor teach in the name of Jeſus.</hi> So, was not that a ſad, and ſinful day, in the time of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin Martyr?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Clarks Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. Hiſt. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> The Proconſul in <hi>Aſia</hi> forbad, that Chriſtians ſhould read any Books that ſpake of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>In this little little Book, thou mayeſt read of a Jeſus; the <hi>Lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of a Jeſus; the <hi>Waſhing</hi> of a Jeſus; whoſe Name is Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to the Mouth; Melody to the Ear, and Muſick to the Heart.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:33854:6"/>
               <hi>Pauls</hi> Epistles, and <hi>Peters</hi> Epiſtles, are Ours, though not in their Inſcriptions, yet in their Benefit. Words paſs away, and are forgotten, when writing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main: Every new Tide, blots out a writing in the Sand; and every new Term, ſhews the former forgotten; but writing deceives even Death it ſelf.</p>
            <p>If this Book ſhould turn to the Good of None, yet ſhall I ſing but to the ſame Tune, that others of Gods Servants have done before Me; witneſs this place among others:
<note place="margin">Iſa. <hi>49.4</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Then I ſaid, I have laboured in vain; I have ſpent my ſtrength for nought, and in vain, yet ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely my Judgement is with the Lord, and my work (or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward) with God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> A pretention to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie
<pb facs="tcp:33854:7"/>every Reader, were as ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous, as his Attempt, who ſtudied to make a Veſtement for the Moon, that might fit her for every Interchange. If (there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) thou beeſt curious, and critical, I cannot pretend to the leaſt hope of pleaſing Thee, for thou wilt (I fear) be find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faults, beſides the faults that are to be found.</p>
            <p>But, leaſt this Epiſtle ſhould ſwell, and become tympanious, I will give it a timely Check.</p>
            <p>As it is true, there is a (ſo) believing, for there muſt be a believing with the Heart; yea,
<note place="margin">Acts <hi>8.37.</hi>
               </note> with the whole Heart; <hi>If thou believeſt with all thine heart, thou mayeſt:</hi> And, as there is a (ſo) repenting,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> for there muſt be <hi>ſorrowing after a godly manner;</hi> or (as the
<pb facs="tcp:33854:7"/>Greek is) <hi>a ſorrowing accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to God:</hi> And,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2</hi> Cor. <hi>7.9.</hi>
               </note> as there is a (ſo) running; <hi>So run,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2</hi> Cor. <hi>9.24</hi>
                  </note> that ye may obtain:</hi> And, as there is a (ſo) doing;
<note place="margin">Matth. <hi>24.46.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed is that Servant, whom his Lord, when he commeth, ſhall find ſo doing;</hi> It is as true, there is a (ſo) reading;
<note place="margin">Acts <hi>8.30.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeſt thou what thou readeſt?
<note place="margin">Mar. <hi>13.14.</hi>
                  </note> And let him that readeth, underſtand.</hi> If, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, thou wouldeſt (ſo) read, look unto Chriſt; For,
<note place="margin">Jo. <hi>15.5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him, thou canſt do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing;</hi> And to the Spirit; For <hi>that ſearcheth all things, yea,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>2.10</hi>
                  </note> the Depths of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now,
<note place="margin">Iſa. <hi>50.4.</hi>
               </note> that (he) <hi>who hath the Tongue of the learned, and knows how to ſpeak a word in ſeaſon to him that is weary,</hi> may ſignally bleſs thy Reading, unto Receiving,
<pb facs="tcp:33854:8"/>and Relliſhing, and Remembring; humbly, and heartily prayeth,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
               <signed>Thy Friend, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, for Jeſus ſake, Richard Mayhew.</signed>
            </closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Vox audita perit, ſed Litera ſcripta manebit.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33854:8"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>LOVING and WASHING.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Rev. 1.5. part thereof.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <q>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto him that loved us, and waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us from our Sins, in his own Blood.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloved! As <hi>Geneſis</hi> begins, ſo the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation</hi> ends, this Book of God, the holy Scriptures of Truth.</p>
               <p>The ending part of this Book, is called <hi>Apocalypſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> (which is the revelation of a ſecret) from a greek word, which ſignifie to reveal a ſecret. Though the Old, and New Teſtament, make but one Book, yet there are many
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33854:9"/>Books in the Old, and the New Teſtament, that contribute to the making up of this one Book. Now, this Book of the <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> is the laſt (but not the leaſt) of the New Teſtament.</p>
               <p>In the Title of this Book, you have an Account of the matter contained therein:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 1.</note> 'Tis called a Revelation: The Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt, which God gave unto him; that is, which God committed unto him as man, for he had it of himſelf, as God.</p>
               <p>In the Context, you have the Perſon ſaluting; the Perſons ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted; and the Salutation it ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lf.</p>
               <p>The Perſon ſaluting.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> That's <hi>John.</hi> But what <hi>John</hi> was He? It was that <hi>John,</hi> that had ſuch intimacy with Jeſus; that <hi>John</hi> that lay ſo much in the Boſom of Jeſus, as if he could not live out of it; that <hi>John,</hi> that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to be an Euangeliſt in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33854:9"/>his Goſpel; an Apoſtle, in his Epiſtles; and a Prophet in this Book of the Revelation. <hi>John,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Perſons ſaluted.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Theſe are the ſeven <hi>Aſiatick</hi> Churches. <hi>John,</hi> To the ſeven Churches in <hi>Aſia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Salutation it ſelf.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you have</p>
               <p>The Matter of it. Grace,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and Peace. Grace, be unto you, and Peace. Grace, and then Peace; not Peace, and then Grace; that's the beſt wear in the World, for it weares not out in wearing; if once, 'tis ever; though it may decay, it cannot dye. Grace, and Peace. Grace, be unto you, and Peace. Grace, and then Peace; the Sun and then the Light.</p>
               <p>Peace; peace of Conſcience, and that's an Anticipation of Glory, a Heaven begun here. Grace, be unto you, and Peace;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33854:10"/>the Sun, and the Light too; the Fire, and the Heat too; Grace, and Peace too; that's the ſubject Matter of the Salu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
               <p>The Original of this Matter.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Here's Grace, and Peace, but where may they be had?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.4. <hi>former part</hi>
                  </note> whence are they derived? where do they Center? from whom are they communicated? from the Trinity in Unity; and Unity in Trinity, Father, Son, and Spirit.</p>
               <p>From the Father,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Grace be unto you and Peace; but from whom?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.4. <hi>mid part.</hi>
                  </note> from him which is, and which was, and which is to come (i. e.) from the Father; from him, whoſe name is <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 6.3.</note> But, by my name <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah,</hi> was I not made known unto them. Which name <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah,</hi> ſignifie no leſs then this, which was, and is, and will be.</p>
               <p>From the Spirit.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And from
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33854:10"/>the ſeven Spirits,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.4. <hi>later part.</hi>
                  </note> which are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Throne. That is (if I miſtake not) from the Spirit, called ſeven Spirits, in regard of his manifold graces, which wrought ſo powerfully in thoſe ſeven Churches, as if a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Spirit had been in each Church. Seven Spirits; ſeven, is a note of perfection. <hi>John</hi> (ſpeaking of the Lamb,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.6.</note> Chriſt Jeſus) ſaith, having ſeven horns, and ſeven eyes, which are the ſeven Spirits of God, ſent forth into all the Earth.</p>
               <p>From the Son.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> And from Jeſus Chriſt; where may this Grace be had? From Jeſus Chriſt; the God of Grace, and the God of Peace. Now follows a Deſcription of Chriſts perſon.</p>
               <p>He is (thee) faithfull witneſs.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> One that fully, and truly, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed Gods will, by himſelf, and his Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:33854:11"/>He is (thee) firſt begotten of the dead.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> That is, he is the firſt that aroſe from the dead, to go to Heaven. <hi>Enoch,</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> ſaw not death; the firſt death; they made a leap over the Grave, and were tranſlated; they were taken into Heaven, but they dyed not. Others were raiſed, and lived here, but died after; neither are their Bodies yet in Heaven: Chriſt, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, is called the firſt begotten, becauſe, the bodily life, which we had by Generation, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored by the Reſurrection; And he is called, the firſt begotten of the dead, becauſe, he had the firſt corporal Reſurrection gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, as Head of the Body the Church. There are ſome that dyed, and went to Heaven, as to Soul, but not as to Body; there are two (<hi>Enoch,</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi>) that dyed not, and are gone to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33854:11"/>Heaven Soul, and Body; but for one that dyed, Chriſt is that onely one that's gone to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, Soul, and Body.</p>
               <p>He is (thee) Prince of the Kings of the Earth.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Ye have an Emphaſis upon every diſtinct branch of the Deſcription; thee faithfull witneſs; thee firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten; and thee Prince; the King of Kings; unto him all the mighty Monarchs of the World ſhall ſtrike Sail; and at his Feet ſhall they all caſt their Scepters, when he ſhall perſonally return from Heaven, to Earth; and be (gloriouſly) crowned, where he was (ignominiouſly) crucified. Thus <hi>John,</hi> ſpeak of Jeſus, by way of Emphaſis, Eminency, and Excellency, concerning Grace, and Peace; they being both in him formally,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>v.</hi> 1.5.</note> as in the Subject of them; and cauſally, as in the Fountain of them, that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33854:12"/>is, in ſhort; Chriſt is the God, and Giver, of Grace, and Peace; which arrives me at my Text, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto him who loved us, and waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us, from our Sins, in his own Blood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beloved! in this Text, you have the Perſon and the Praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate.</p>
               <p>The Perſon.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Him; or, who; that is, Chriſt. Unto Him.</p>
               <p>The Praedicate.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Who loved us, and waſhed us from our Sins, in his own Blood. Now, here in you have</p>
               <p>The great Affection of the Perſon;
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> that's Loving. Who loved.</p>
               <p>The greateſt Demonſtration of this Affection;
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> that's waſhing. And waſhed: who loved, and waſhed: Loved and then waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; not waſhed, and then loved. And herein, you have</p>
               <p>The Perſons that are waſhed.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:33854:12"/>Us. But who are theſe? Theſe (properly) are the ſeven Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, for (unto) theſe do <hi>John</hi> write; and (of) theſe do <hi>John</hi> ſpeak; Us: I ſay, theſe (expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vely) but not (excluſively;) that is, Us, and all that have obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed like precious Faith with us, as the grand Apoſtle of the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion wordeth it.
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Petr.</hi> 1.1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>That (from which) they are waſhed. Sin; yea, Sins.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Who loved us, and waſhed us from our Sins.</p>
               <p>That (by which) they are waſhed. Blood; not water,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> but Bood; yea, his Blood; yea,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> his own Blood; or, the Blood of himſelf; in his own Blood; or, the Blood of himſelf. Who loved us, and waſhed us, from our Sins, in his own Blood.</p>
               <p>The words (thus) divided, from (them) theſe Meditations may be deduced.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:33854:13"/>That Chriſt hath a peculiar People,
<note place="margin">Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and a peculiar love for his peculiar People. Us; Not All, but Us; not Moſt, but Us; not every Individual, but Us; and theſe loved, who loved Us.</p>
               <p>That Chriſt waſheth,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> whom he loveth, and that from their Sins, in his own Blood. And waſhed us from our Sins, in his own Blood.</p>
               <p>That Chriſt hath a peculiar People,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Meditat.</hi> 1.</note> and a peculiar Love for this peculiar People.</p>
               <p>I begin with this, and ſhall engage it as I am more, or leſs, under a divine Gale, and Guſt. Now, if the moſt excellent Glory pleaſe to ſmile a Metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical Diſcourſe unto ſpiritual Advantage, I ſhall digeſt my Diſcourſe into this Method; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring</p>
               <p>Whether Chriſt hath a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar People?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:33854:13"/>Whether Chriſt hath a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Love,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> for this peculiar People?</p>
               <p>What uſe may be made of this,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> That Chriſt hath a peculiar Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and a peculiar Love for his peculiar People?</p>
               <p>Whether Chriſt hath a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar People?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> That God, and Chriſt, have a People; a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar People; a People, above any other People; a People, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all other People, is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. Thus God, and Chriſt had, under the Old Teſtament, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs theſe places.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou art a holy People unto the Lord thy God, and the Lord hath choſen thee to be a peculiar Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple unto himſelf, ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that are upon the Earth,</hi> Deut. 14.2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Lord hath avouched thee this day, to be his peculiar Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as he hath promiſed thee,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33854:14"/>and that thou ſhouldeſt keep all his Commandements,</hi> Deut. 26.18.</p>
               <p>Thus God, and Chriſt (alſo) had under the New Teſtament, wiſneſs theſe places.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who gave himſelf for us, that he might reaeem us from all ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and purifie to himſelf a peculiar People, zealous of good works,</hi> Tit. 2.14.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But ye are a choſen generation, a royal Prieſthood, a peculiar Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that ye ſhould ſhew forth the praiſes (or vertues) of him,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> who hath called you out of darkneſs, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his marvellous light,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.9.</p>
               <p>But take one place more, which comprehend the peculiar People of God, and Chriſt, both under the Old, and New Teſtament. <hi>For Jah hath choſen to himſelf</hi> Jacob, <hi>and</hi> Iſrael <hi>for his inheritance,</hi> Pſalm. 135.4. So that what was promiſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Old Teſtament, is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33854:14"/>by Chriſt, in redeeming, and purifying his peculiar Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple under the New.</p>
               <p>Whether Chriſt hath a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Love,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>But,</hi> 2.</note> for this peculiar Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Beloved! I ſhall endeavour an evincement of this Truth, in giving you a Taſt of what manner of Love Chriſt hath to his People. As Chriſt hath a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar People, which I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready proved, ſo he hath a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Love to this peculiar People; now, this will appear by the Quantity, or Meaſure of it; and by the Quality, or Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of it.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> In reference to the Meaſure of it. There's the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of Love, which is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural; and the Grace of Love, which is ſupernatural.</p>
               <p>There's the Affection of Love,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and that's natural, This is, or ought to be in all Men, or Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Hath not the Husband a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33854:15"/>natural Affection to the Wiſe, and Children? Hath not the Wife a natural Affection to the Husband, and Children? The Apoſtle (<hi>Rom.</hi> 1.31.) reckons, and ranks thoſe among capital, and cardinal Sinners, that are without natural Affection.</p>
               <p>There's the Grace of Love,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and that's ſupernatural. Now, the Grace of Love, is in Chriſt formally, and cauſally.</p>
               <p>Formally.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Love, is in Chriſt, as the ſubject of it;
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 4.8.</note> he is the God of it. God is Love. Not onely lovely, and loving, but Love in the Abſtract. God, is Love.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jo.</hi> 1.1.</note> Chriſt, is God. <hi>In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God.</hi> As is the Height of the Lover, ſo is the Height of the Love. The Moraliſts judge of the Magnitude of Crimes, by the Perſons againſt whom they
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33854:15"/>are committed: And, as it was ſaid of <hi>Gideon,</hi> as the Man is, ſo is his Strength; Thus, it may be ſaid of Chriſt, as He is,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.6.</note> ſo is his Love; but he is wonderfull, his name ſhall be called wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; ſo is his Love; as his name is wonderful, ſo is his Love. Chriſt is a Bundle of Love; all the diſperſed Excellencies, and Loves, that are in the World, meet in him, as all the Lines meet in the Center.</p>
               <p>Cauſally. Love, is in Chriſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> as the Fountain of it. Beloved! As Chriſt is the God of Love, ſo he is the Giver of Love, to this my Text ſpeaks, who loved us.</p>
               <p>In reference to the Manner of it.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>But</hi> 2.</note> As this appears by the Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, or Meaſure of it; ſo it appears by the Quality, or Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of it. Now, in a Diſcuſſion of the Manner of Chriſts Love,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:33854:16"/>to his peculiar People, there will be a Diſcourry of it to be a peculiar Love.</p>
               <p>But what Manner of Love,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion. </seg>
                  </label> is Chriſts Love?</p>
               <p>What manner of Love,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution. </seg>
                  </label> is Chriſts Love, is that the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion?
<note place="margin">What man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Love.</note> Give me leave (then) to ſay, 'tis much more eaſie to ſay, what it is not, then what it is: My Line is too ſhort to ſound this Bottom; what's a Muſcle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhel to empty an Ocean! In Chriſt, there are deep Riches that cannot be ſounded; and rich Deeps that cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted; I ſhall therefore, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe but a Taſt of this Love.</p>
               <p>Chriſts Love,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> is attracting Love.
<note place="margin">Attracting</note> 'Tis no more connatural to the Loadſtone, to draw Iron to it; then for the Love of Chriſt, to draw Love out of the Chriſtian. 'Tis ſaid of <hi>Mary Magdalene,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 7.4.7.</note> that much was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33854:16"/>her, for ſhe loved much. Not that her much Loving, was the cauſe of her much For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving; but Chriſt forgiving her much, ſhe loved much.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11.4.</note> I drew them with Cords of a man, with bands of Love. As the Banner Chriſt diſplay, ſo the Cord by which he draw, is Love. His Love hath a Magnetick vertue.</p>
               <p>Chriſts Love,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> is abounding Love.
<note place="margin">Abounding.</note> Had <hi>David</hi> a Cup run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning over? Oh what hath Chriſt then the Lord of <hi>David!</hi> But, <hi>David</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou prepareſt a Table before me, in the preſence of mine Enemies: thou anointeſt mine head with Oyl; my Cup run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth over.</hi> Beloved! The Cup of Chriſts Love, is not only full, but it runs over; This <hi>Nilus</hi> overflows her Banks in Winter, as well as Summer. Chriſt, loveth his, as he loveth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; Yea, he ſeemeth to love
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:33854:17"/>his above himſelf, for, he lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them, and out of Love dyeth for them. <hi>I lay down my life for the Sheep.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Je.</hi> 10.15.</note> Now, hath not Chriſt a peculiar People? and is not this a peculiar Love, that he hath for this peculiar People?</p>
               <p>Chriſts Love,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> is abiding Love. Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Abiding.</note> doth not carry it towards a Chriſtian, as <hi>Ammon</hi> towards <hi>Tamar</hi> (2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.15.) who ſeemed to love one day, and hate another, who (ſeemingly) loved one hour, and (really) hated another. 'Tis ſaid, the Man was ſick for her, till he had ſatisfied his Luſt upon her, but then he hated her exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly; or (according to the Margent) he hated her with great hatred greatly; So that the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tred, wherewith he hated her, was greater then the Love, wherewith he loved her: But
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:33854:17"/>Chriſts Love, is an abiding Love;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jo.</hi> 13.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Having lov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d his own which were in the World, he loved them unto the end;</hi> that is, World without end. Chriſts Love, is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſting, yea, an everlaſting Love; this Love will laſt, as long as the Chriſtian laſteth; as long as Chriſt laſteth.
<note place="margin">Semèl &amp; Simùl.</note> ONCE and EVER, is Loves Motto. Chriſt, (once) loving (ever) loveth; is not this (then) a peculiar Love?</p>
               <p>Chriſts Love,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> is a conſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Love.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Conſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14.</note> 
                  <hi>The Love of Chriſt conſtraineth us, becauſe we thus judge: that if one dyed for all, then were all dead.</hi> The Love of Chriſt conſtraineth; or, hem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in; keepeth in. The Love of Chriſt hath a mighty In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, it hemmeth in;
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in, as the Greek word ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth. It is a Metaphor taken from a Creature that is hemmed in, ſo that there is no evaſion.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:33854:18"/>
                  <hi>Go into the high wayes,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 14.23.</note> and hedge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and compel them to come in, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> my Houſe may be filled.</hi> Not i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a way of haſty violence, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a way of gracious Influence: O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> go, and preach my Love, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this ſhall have a ſingular, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignal Influence! Is not th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (then) a peculiar Love?</p>
               <p>Chriſts Love,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
                  <note place="margin">Delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> is a delightin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Love. Love, is Chriſts Element and he is in his Element whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he is loving, and manifeſtin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his Love.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 8.31.</note> 
                  <hi>His Delights were wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> the Sons of Men</hi> There is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Love of pity; thus Chriſt be held the profound Moraliſt, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> loved him: There is (alſo) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Love of Complacence, and De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> light.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mich. ult.</hi> 18.</note> 
                  <hi>He retaineth not his Ange<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> for ever, becauſe he delighted i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Mercy.</hi> Is not this (now) a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Love?</p>
               <p>Chriſts Love,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/>
                  <note place="margin">Overcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</note> is overcome ming Love. If Chriſt lay Seige
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:33854:18"/>to a Soul in a way of Mercy; in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> way of tender Mercy; in a way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f Bowels of tender Mercy, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>kes the Soul captive. Belov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d! Chriſt hath a better way to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke Souls, then Generals have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o take Caſtles, &amp;c. they lay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eige, and are neceſſitated many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imes to ſtorm the Caſtle; to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cals the Walls &amp;c. But Chriſt, when he lays Siege in a way of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſcriminating Love, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ently works the Souls unto a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>endition; he makes the Soul willing to give up it ſelf to him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y way of Surrender; as it takes Chriſt for Saviour, ſo it gives <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p it ſelf to Chriſt as Soveraign. A <hi>Roman</hi> General, beſieging a Town, a Friend of his asked <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Account of his proceedings; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o whom he replied in three words: <hi>I came; beheld,
<note place="margin">Veni; Vidi: Vici.</note> and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came.</hi> Thus Chriſt, make a quick Diſpatch with the Soul; He
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33854:19"/>did but ſpeak for <hi>Matthew,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he had him: <hi>Mathew,</hi> was ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering the Emperors Tolls, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tributs; now Chriſt did bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſay to him,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Follow me,</hi> but h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> aroſe, and followed him. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſooner did Chriſt lay ſiege to <hi>Zacheus,</hi> but he made a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt upon him, and made him a Captive to his Love;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 19.5, 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> haſt</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>and come down, for I must abide at thy houſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> And he made haſt, and came down, and received him joyfully.</hi> Chriſt ſoon made his way into the houſe of <hi>Zacheus,</hi> and into the heart of <hi>Zacheus</hi> too.
<note place="margin">Amor om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia vincit.</note> The Love of Man may overcome many things, as Hunger, and Thirſt, and Nakedneſs, &amp;c. but the Love of Chriſt (who is God-Man) overcome all things; this make a Conqueſt upon the heart, and make that a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to God, and Grace; is
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:33854:19"/>not this (then) a peculiar Love.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſts Love,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Pſal.</hi> 59.10.</note> is preventing Love. <hi>The God of my mercy ſhall prevent me.</hi> Mark the expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; 'Tis the God of Mercy that prevent, and he prevent in a way of Mercy. Beloved! To be delivered out of an evil, is a Mercy; but to be prevented from falling into any evil, is a greater Mercy: To be delivered out of an ſickneſs is good; but to be prevented from falling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſickneſs, is better: To be delivered in great danger, is a great Mercy; but to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented from being endangered, is greater Mercy.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 79.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Oh remember not againſt us former Iniquities, let thy tender Mercies ſpeedily prevent us, for we are brought very low.</hi> 'Tis the God of Mercy and the Mercy of God, that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, and is not this (then) pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Mercy?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:33854:20"/>Chriſts Love,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> is preſerving Love.
<note place="margin">Preſerving.</note> Chriſts Love, is preſervative Amulet; the beſt preſervative in the World againſt poyſoning; againſt infecting; againſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying. <hi>Neah,</hi> and thoſe with him are Arcked.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 7.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Come thou, and all thy houſe into the Arke.</hi> God, prepared them an Arke, that they rode ſecurely, when the waters covered all the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains: Arked, they were, and ſo preſerved they were: <hi>Peter,</hi> while upon the water, hath his head kept above water: Chriſt out of Love to <hi>Peter,</hi> preſerve <hi>Peter.</hi> God (if I may ſo ſpeak) rains Hell, out of Heaven upon <hi>Sodom,</hi> but <hi>Lot</hi> is preſerved: Though the lot of <hi>Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> was caſt in <hi>So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vivus in ſepulchro;</hi> Baſil.</note> the Man is preſerved, <hi>Zoar</hi> opens unto him. As <hi>Peter</hi> was preſerved above water, ſo <hi>Jonah</hi> was preſerved under wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; a Whale (the greateſt won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:33854:20"/>in the Deep) houſeth him. And, as <hi>Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> was preſerved from flames,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.21.27.</note> ſo the <hi>Three Children</hi> were preſerved in flames. Oh my Soul, glut thy ſelf with a ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, and a heavenly wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment! what, preſerved above water, and under water! what, preſerved from flames, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der flames! Is not this peculiar Love?</p>
               <p>Chriſts Love, is Poſing Love.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/>
                  <note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſing.</note> Beloved! Chriſts Love, is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove expreſſion; the greateſt <hi>Cicero,</hi> and <hi>Demosthen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> in the World; the greateſt Logician, and Rhetorician in the World; the greateſt Oracle, and Orator in the World, is not able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Chriſts Love to the Life. Yea Sirs, let me ſay, Chriſts Love, is not only above Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, but above Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and Conception. We uſe to ſay, Man is vaſter in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33854:21"/>then in Expreſſion; but Chriſts Love poſeth not only Expreſſion, but Conception. <hi>Eye hath not ſeen,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9.</note> nor ear keard, neither hath it entred into the heart, the things that God hath prepared for them that love him.</hi> Chriſts Love, is a Love that paſſeth knowledge. And to know the Love of Chriſt, that paſſeth knowledge,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 3 19.</note> 
                  <hi>that ye might be filled with all the Fulneſs of God.</hi> The Line of Nature; Yea, the Line of Grace, is not able to ſound this Depth; Is not this (then) a peculiar Love?</p>
               <p>Chriſts Love,
<note place="margin">Laſtly. <hi>Surpaſſing.</hi>
                  </note> is ſurpaſſing Love. Oh Souls! Chriſts Love out-bids, and out-vies all other Loves, and that in a manifold Reſpect. Suffer me to give you (who have taſted that the Lord is gracious) a Taſt of the Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parableneſs of Chriſts Love.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> In reſpect of the freeneſs of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:33854:21"/>it. Wine, and Milk; yea, Grace, and Glory, may be had,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa</hi> 84 11.</note> with out Money, and without price. He giveth Grace, and Glory. Beloved! You have (and that to the Life) the Portraiture of a perſon in his Naturals (<hi>Ezeck</hi> 16 6) <hi>When I paſſed by thee, and ſaw thee polluted in thine own Blood;</hi> or according to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent) troden under Foot in thine own Blood; is not this a ſad ſtate, for a man to be tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den under Foot? for a man to be tumbling, and wallowing in his own Blood? But what then? Did Chriſt leave the Man as he found him? No; I ſaid unto thee, when thou waſt in thy Blood, live; Yea, I ſaid unto thee, when thou waſt in thy blood, live. There was no Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit here; nor Motive here; there was nothing but free-grace here; meer Mercy here. Now, was
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33854:22"/>the time of the Creatures great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt defilement,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezeck.</hi> 16.8.</note> and deformity; and yet this was the time of Chriſts Love. Now, when I paſſed by thee, and looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee, behold, thy time was the time of Love; and I ſpread my skirt over thee, and covered thy nakedneſs; Yea, I ſwear unto thee, and entred into a Covenant with thee, ſaith <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah</hi> God, and thou becammeſt Mine; Is not this a peculiar Love?</p>
               <p>In reſpect of the firſtneſs of it.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Chriſt, is firſt in Love. Chriſt, loves, before he is lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 4.19.</note> We love him; why? <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he firſt loved us.</hi> Chriſts Love is primary; Ours ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary: His, the cauſe; Ours, but the effect. Had not Chriſt fired our hearts with Love, we had never beſtowed a ſpark of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Affection upon him. Had
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:33854:22"/>not Chriſt (firſt) loved us, we lived, and dyed, without loving him. Chriſt loveth before lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; is not this (then) peculiar Love?</p>
               <p>In reſpect of the Sameneſs of it.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Chriſt, and thoſe that are Chriſts, have the ſame Love.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jo.</hi> 17.26.</note> 
                  <hi>I have declared unto them thy name, and I will declare it, that the love where with thou haſt loved me, may be in them, and I in them.</hi> Is not this (now) pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Love?</p>
               <p>In reſpect of the Sureneſs of it. As it is the (ſame) Love,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> ſo it is a (ſure) Love.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Incline your ears, and come unto me; hear, and your Souls ſhall live;</hi> but what then? <hi>and I will make an, even laſting Covenant with you. even the (ſure) mercies of David;</hi> Thou mayſt looſe thy Wife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looſe thy Child; looſe thy E<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtate; yea, looſe thy Life, but
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:33854:23"/>thou canſt not looſe this Love; Is it not (then) a peculiar Love?</p>
               <p>In reſpect of the Goodneſs of it.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.5.</note> This Love, is Life; <hi>In thy Favour is Life.</hi> Yea, Sirs, this Love, is better then Life; better then Lifes;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 63.3.</note> ſo the Hebrew: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thy loving kindneſs is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then Lifes,
<note place="margin">Mechajim.</note> 
                  <hi>my lips ſhall praiſe Thee.</hi> Chriſts Love, is better then Life; then Lives; that is, 'tis better then Life it ſelf, and all ſorts of Life whatſoever: 'Tis better then Life, and all the concerns of Life; 'tis bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then many; better then all Lives bundled together; bound up together. Is natural Life no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing? Is not life the beſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſyllabe in the World? but, this is a ſpiritual Life; yea, this is an eternal Life; And, is not this (then) a peculiar Love?</p>
               <p>In reſpect of the Greatneſs of it.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> All Love may be reduced
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33854:23"/>to three Heads; Carnal; Moral; Spiritual; And yet Chriſts Love out-bids any of theſe; out-vies all theſe. But, to theſe diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</p>
               <p>Carnal.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Now this Carnal Love, may fall under three heads; the World; Self; and Sin.</p>
               <p>The World. Souls!
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Chriſts Love to Thee (if thou beeſt Chriſts) is greater then thy Love to the World have been. The love of the World, is a great Sin, and looks like a Sin incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the truth of Grace.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Jo</hi> 2.15.</note> If any Man, (any one, ſo the Greek) Man or Woman, love the World, the Love of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is not in him; or her.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.10.</note> The love of Money is called the root of all evil. But now, Chriſts love to Thee, is greater then thy love have been to the world; ſo ſay my Text, <hi>Who loved us,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:33854:24"/>and waſhed us.</hi> Here's waſhing, as well as loving; yea, waſhing, the Effect, and Conſequent of loving; Is not this (then) a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Love?</p>
               <p>Self.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Chriſts love to Thee (if thou beeſt Chriſts) is greater then thy love have been to thy Self. Self-Love is a great Sin, for a Man is to deny himſelf, not to love himſelf.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.24.</note> 
                  <hi>If any Man will come after Me let him deny himſelf.</hi> But now, Chriſts Love to Thee, is greater then thy Love hath been to thy Self; witneſs my Text: <hi>Who loved us, and waſhed us.</hi> Here is loving, and waſhing out of Love; 'tis (now) a peculiar Love.</p>
               <p>Sin.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Chriſts love to Thee (if thou beeſt Chriſts) is greater then thy love have been to Sin. Thy love; and my love, to ſin, have been great; greatly great: <hi>Lovers of pleaſure,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.4.</note> more then
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:33854:24"/>Lovers of God.</hi> Thou haſt ſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed diverſe luſts, and pleaſures; thy Soul have been a Veſſel of Sin, and a Vaſſal unto Satan; but now Chriſts love to Thee, is greater then thy love have been to Sin; witneſs the Text: <hi>Who loved us, and waſhed us,</hi> but from what? From our Sins in his own Blood. Is not this (then) a peculiar Love?</p>
               <p>Moral.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> As Chriſts Love is greater then carnal, ſo then Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. Chriſts Love is greater then the Love of the Maſter to the Servant.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>For</hi> 1.</note> The Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rions Love, was great to his Servant; 'tis expreſly ſaid, that he had a Servant, who was dear unto him, but he was ſick, and ready to dye; Now, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Jeſus,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 7.2, 3.</note> he ſent unto him the Elders of the Jews, beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him that he would come, and heal his Servant. The Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:33854:25"/>Love was great, deſiring his Servant might be healed; but Chriſts was greater,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 7.10.</note> for he heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Servant. They found the Servant whole.</p>
               <p>Chriſts Love is greater then the Love of the Father to the Child.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
                  <hi>Jacob</hi> Love to <hi>Benjamin</hi> was great; the Fathers life, was bound up in the Lads life. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> love to <hi>Abſalom</hi> was great;
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.33.</note> if not too great: <hi>That I had ayed for thee, oh Abſalom, my Son, my Son!</hi> But Chriſts is greater. When my Father, and my Mother forſake me then <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hovah</hi> will gather me.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 27.10.</note> When my Father caſt me out of his Arms, and my Mother caſt me off her knees, then <hi>Jehovah</hi> will gather me into the Arms of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginningleſs, and endleſs Mercy.</p>
               <p>Chriſts Love is greater then the Love of the Mother to the Child.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The Mothers Love, is a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:33854:25"/>great Love; if not the greateſt Love.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa</hi> 49.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Can a Woman forget her ſucking child, from having com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion on the child of her womb?</hi> Is there ſuch a Women among Women? Yea, they may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get, yet will I not forget Thee.</p>
               <p>Chriſts Love is greater then the Love of the Husband to the Wife. Conjug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l Love,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> is (at leaſt ought to be) great Love. The Love of <hi>Abraham,</hi> to <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah</hi> was great; of <hi>Iſaac</hi> to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becca</hi> was great; of <hi>Jacob</hi> to <hi>Rackel</hi> was great; of <hi>Elkanah,</hi> to <hi>Hannah</hi> was great; of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus</hi> to his <hi>Livia</hi> was great, who dyed in the Embraceme is of her, with theſe words: <hi>Livia, noſtri Conjugii memoreſto, vive, &amp; vale;</hi> which may thus be Engliſhed: <hi>Livia, remember we were one, live, and farewell.</hi> Man, and Wife, are one fleſh; and (if both be living) one Spirit,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:33854:26"/>ſo that this Love muſt needs be great; but Chriſts is greater. <hi>Husbands,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.25.</note> love your Wives, as Chriſt loved the Church, and gave himſelf for it.</hi> Where is there a Husband, that gives himſelf for his Wife? that gives himſelf to death for his Wife? Or, if he ſhould, what would it ſignifie? She could never ſay (with the Text) <hi>who loved me, and waſhed me, from my Sins in his Blood:</hi> This muſt not be ſaid, of any blood, but Chriſts; is not this (then) a peculiar Love?</p>
               <p>Spiritual.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Chriſts Love is greater then the Spiritual Love of Chriſtians. <hi>Jonathans</hi> love to <hi>David</hi> was great; and <hi>Davids</hi> love to <hi>Jonathan</hi> was great; but Chriſts is greater: what's a ſpark to the Furnace? a drop to the Ocean? Such, is the Love of Man, to the Love of Chriſt, God manifeſt in the fleſh. 'Tis true,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:33854:26"/>
                  <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks very honourably of <hi>Jonathans</hi> Love:
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.26.</note> 
                  <hi>Thy Love to me have been wonderfull, paſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Love of Women:</hi> But Chriſts Love is greater; Chriſts Love is greateſt.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jo.</hi> 14.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Greater Love hath no Man then this, that a Man lay down his life for his Friend.</hi> Chriſt laid down his life for Enemies; as Enemies; when, and while Enemies; Is not this (now) a peculiar Love?</p>
               <p>What uſe may be made of this,
<note place="margin">Laſtly.</note> that Chriſt hath a peculiar Love, for his peculiar People?</p>
               <p>Hath Chriſt a peculiar Love for his peculiar People?
<note place="margin">USE.</note> This (then) may be uſeful by way of Caution; by way of Comfort; by way of Councel.</p>
               <p>Is Chriſts Love,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> a peculiar Love?
<note place="margin">By way of Caution.</note> take heed (then) of turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Love into Luſt; and loving kindneſs, into laſciviouſneſs. To do evil, that good may
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:33854:27"/>come; and to be ſinful, becauſe God is merciful; and to be luſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, becauſe Chriſt is Love-ful, is the Sophiſtry of the Prince of Darkneſs. Doſt argue from Grace to Sin? from Love to Luſt? from Mercy, to Iniquity? from Immunity, unto Impiety? this is the Dialect of Hell, and the Sophiſtry of the Prince of Darkneſs.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.8.</note> Oh how do the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle thunder againſt ſuch! we are ſlanderouſly reported, and ſome affirm that we ſay: Let us do evil, that good may come, whoſe damnation is juſt.</p>
               <p>Art loved:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> be joyous, Soul, thou art more then a Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour through him that loveth.
<note place="margin">By way of Comfort.</note> Oh you that have the Love of Chriſt, ſhed abroad in your hearts by the Spirit of Chriſt, this Text as a Cordial under your fainting Fits: <hi>Who loved us.</hi> Art tempted, or troubled? pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:33854:27"/>or panged? diſtreſſed, or diſſerted? yet loved;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Me Duce, vinces. Rom.</hi> 8.37.</note> 
                  <hi>who loved us.</hi> Nay, <hi>in all theſe things we are more then Conquerors;</hi> but how? <hi>through him that loved us.</hi> Not only Conquerors, but more then Conquerors. It is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound word, and ſignifies more then ſimply to overcome:
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> we greatly overcome; we over, and above overcome; we over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come above meaſure, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding gloriouſly: we do more then overcome; we do Over-overcome, as the Greek ſeem to read it: It may well be read thus. But in all theſe things we Over-overcome through him that loved us. In all theſe things; but what things were theſe? Theſe things, ye may run, and read (<hi>Rom.</hi> 8.35) <hi>What ſhall ſeparate us from the Love of God? ſhall Tribulation? or Diſtreſs? or Perſecution? or Famine? or
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:33854:28"/>Nakedneſs? or Peril? or Sword?</hi> Here are ſeven bitter Diſhes, and ſhall theſe? No; In all theſe things we do Over-overcome. Is not any one of theſe Diſhes enough for any pallate in the World? yet, not one of theſe; not any of theſe; yea, not all theſe, ſhall ſeparate from the Love of God; But, in all theſe things we do Over-overcome; but how? through him that lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us. Now, that thy Cup may be filled with Joy, and Peace, like the water pots of <hi>Galilee,</hi> up to the very Brim; ſuffer me to tell thee, that Chriſts Love is the moſt ſutable, and ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Cordial.</p>
               <p>Chriſts Love,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> is the moſt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Cordial. Thoſe Cordials, are moſt efficacious, that are moſt natural, and moſt ſuiting the Spirits.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20.</note> Chriſts Love, is the Chriſtians Life. <hi>I live, yet not
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:33854:28"/>I, but Chriſt liveth in me.</hi> Chriſts Love, falls in with the Life of a Chriſtian, and therefore moſt ſutable.</p>
               <p>Chriſts Love,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> is the moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Cordial. As Gods Love (when he gave Chriſt) is put for all Cauſes.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jo.</hi> 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>So God loved the World, that he gave his only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son.</hi> So Chriſts Love (when Chriſtians get comfort) is put for all Cordials. Is not that a lofty, as well as a lovely Expreſſion, of the great Doctor of the Gentiles?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.38, 39.</note> 
                  <hi>For I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that neither Death, nor Life, nor Angels; nor Principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, nor Powers, Nor things preſent, nor things to come, Nor Height, nor Depth, nor any other creature, ſhall be able to ſeparate us from the love of God, which is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord.</hi> Soul! Chriſts Love, contain in it the ſum of the Goſpel, Chriſt being
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:33854:29"/>the ſum of the Goſpel, and Love the ſum of Chriſt. God, ſo lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the World, that he gave Chriſt, and Chriſt ſo loved the World, that he gave himſelf, contain in it the Pith, and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, of all the Goſpel. This little word <hi>(Love)</hi> written in the golden letters of free-Grace in the blood of Jeſus Chriſt, is an Epitomy of the Goſpel. The <hi>Life</hi> of Chriſt, was a perfect Mirror of his <hi>Love;</hi> every acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it was full of Love; and if we put all the Actions of his life together we may conclude, that he was not born ſo much to <hi>Live,</hi> as to <hi>Love.</hi> Was there a word that dropped from his Lips, but was ſull of <hi>Love?</hi> And, as for his works, they all ſpeak <hi>Love</hi> ſo loud, that the deafeſt ear may hear it. Should we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin at the Temple, where Chriſt diſputed with the <hi>Doctors,</hi> and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:33854:29"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>low him to the Mount, where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> was crucified by the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers, we ſhould ſee all the way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ewed with <hi>Love-Reſes.</hi> Now, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> loved? then (this) Chriſt, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hy) Chriſt; and (this) <hi>Love<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hy) <hi>Love<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and is not this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tter of Joy? Go away (then) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d be filled with Joy, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ace, through Believing.</p>
               <p>Oh but there are <hi>Achans</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>!
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> 
                  <hi>Sauls</hi> within! the Sons of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erviab</hi> within! Oh there are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>any Blots in my <hi>Scutcheon!</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>any <hi>Weeds</hi> in my Garden! <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uch <hi>Rubbiſh</hi> in my Houſe! <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>any <hi>Holes</hi> in my Coat! much <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ven</hi> in my Heart! Oh no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eart like unto Mine!</p>
               <p>Soul!
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Solut. </seg>
                  </label> Chriſts <hi>Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> is greater <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en thy <hi>Luſt,</hi> and his <hi>Mercy,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en thine <hi>Iniquity.</hi> If the <hi>Sun,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e not fuller of <hi>Light,</hi> nor the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> fuller of <hi>Water,</hi> then (thy) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eart, and (my) heart, of the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:33854:30"/>Remains of Sin, yet Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Love</hi> ballanced againſt this, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> weigh it down.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> 34.6.7</note> 
                  <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ugh God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits Iniquity to the third, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> fourth Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eration, yet he ke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Mercy for thouſands; for the ſands of Generations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh but if things be ſo,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> am I thus? Oh why am I th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> reſponding? and thus doubtin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and thus drooping?</p>
               <p>Endeavour thy Souls Reſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rection by a ſerious Conſide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Solut. </seg>
                  </label>
               </p>
               <p>Conſider;
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Chriſt (out of Lov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gave himſelf (for) Thee: W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> loved us;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20.</note> what then? and ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> himſelf for us.</p>
               <p>Conſider;
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Chriſt (out of Love gave himſelf (to) Thee. I giv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> unto them eternal life. No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt, in giving eternal life giveth himſelf,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 5.20.</note> for He is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> true God, and eternal life. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> how may you ſing like Larks
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:33854:30"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at have been mourning like <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ves,</hi> and groaning like <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> that can (in truth) ſay, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l this <hi>Truth, who loved us!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hath Chriſt a peculiar Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
                  <note place="margin">By way of Counſel.</note> and a peculiar love for this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>culiar People? ſuffer then the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ords of Exhortation. Now, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is uſe, hath a double Aſpect, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d looks to thoſe that are not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ved; and then to thoſe that are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ved.</p>
               <p>Art not loved?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Tremble (then) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou mayſt be an Object of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ne hatred. Is Chriſts love,
<note place="margin">To the Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved.</note> a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eculiar Love? ſuch a Love as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath been preached, and infini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly more? and art not thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oncerned in it? Haſt not thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Tast</hi> of it? Oh how canſt thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at, or drink? Oh how canſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hou reſt day, or night? I knew <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he time, when I feared every <hi>Drop</hi> would poyſon me, and every <hi>Crum</hi> choak me; when
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:33854:31"/>I feared the <hi>Earth</hi> would op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and ſwallow me up in the <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and that my <hi>Bea</hi> would beco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> my <hi>Grave</hi> at <hi>Night,</hi> and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> becauſe I had not a <hi>Taſt</hi> of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> peculiar <hi>Love.</hi> Oh Soul! h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may that Scripture (which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins ſweetly,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.13.</note> but ends ſharp <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in thine ears? <hi>Jacob, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> I loved but Eſau have I but</hi> It ſeems all are not loved w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the ſame love; but, as ſome a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Objects of infinite Love, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> others are Objects of infini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Hatred. Oh how amazing, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> amuzing would this be, if Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould ſay concerning Thee, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Ahab</hi> did concerning the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet? There is one <hi>Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>jab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> but I hate him. There is ſuch Man, but I hate him; and ſud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a Woman, but I hate her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> There is ſuch a Child, but I hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him; and ſuch a Servant, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I hate her. No more are loved,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:33854:31"/>then are waſhed; at leaſt, ſhall be waſhed; which is implied, if not expreſſed in this Text, and Truth, <hi>Who loved us, and waſhed us from our Sins,</hi> in the Blood of Himſelf.</p>
               <p>Art loved by Chriſt?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                  <note n="2" place="margin">To the loved.</note> Be much more (then) in Love with Chriſt! Oh Soul, love Chriſt more! Love Chriſt moſt! There can be no exceſs in Love to Chriſt; there may be a ſinful ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of Love to a Husband; of Love to a Wife; of love to a Child; but there cannot be a ſinful exceſs in love to a Chriſt. May not Chriſt ſay to Thee, as he did to <hi>Peter?
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jo.</hi> 21.15</note> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter loveſt skou me more then theſe?</hi> Loveſt thou me more then thou loveſt theſe? Or, loveſt thou me more then theſe love me?</p>
               <p>Art loved by Chriſt?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Be much more (then) in Love with thoſe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:33854:32"/>that are Chriſts. Doſt love the Father, and not the Child? Doſt love the Head, and not the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy? Doſt love the Mediator, and not the Member? Doſt love Chriſt, and not thoſe that are Chriſts.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 4.11.</note> The Apoſtle (who ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to me to be as it were) a compound of Love, and whoſe Love ſeemed to be his Maſter-Grace, hath made this uſe to my hands. Beloved! if God ſo lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us, we ought (alſo) to love one another.</p>
               <p>Art loved by Chriſt?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Dread (then) a ſinning againſt this Love. Oh who ſhould ſin againſt that Chriſt, whoſe <hi>Looks</hi> are <hi>Loves,</hi> whoſe <hi>Love,</hi> is Life! Yea, better then <hi>Life!</hi> As this Love cannot be ſinned away, ſo it ſhould not be ſinned againſt. A ſubject of Love, is moſt ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, both to the Hand, and Pen of Chriſt; he wiſhes rather to
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:33854:32"/>write in Honey, then in Gall; and to draw golden lines of Love, then to draw bloody lines of wrath; now, ſhall this Love be ſinned againſt? what Uſe, therefore, the Apoſtle makes of the Day of Chriſt, I may make of the <hi>Love</hi> of Chriſt, <hi>what manner of Perſons ought ye to be in all holy converſation, and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Art loved by Chriſt?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Ballance (then) the Love of Chriſt againſt all thy Sighs, and Sobs; Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, and Sufferings. Beloved! thoſe that are loved, with a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing, and peculiar Love, are not exempted from Sigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Sobbings; from Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing, and ſuffering; yet bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance Chriſts Love under all Theſe. For inſtance</p>
               <p>Art afflicted? yet loved.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Oh ſay the Soul, I can look no way, look no day, but I may ſay,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:33854:33"/>
                  <hi>Gad,</hi> a Troop commeth! a Troop of affliction commeth! <hi>I am the Man that have ſeen af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.1.</note> by the Rod of his wrath.</hi> Well, art afflicted? yet loved. <hi>In all their affliction he was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſa.</hi> 69.9.</note> and the Angel of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence ſaved them.</hi> In all their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, he was afflicted: That is, he was affected with their affliction; and they had his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, under their Affliction.</p>
               <p>Art tempted?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> yet loved. Oh ſay the Soul, I am tempted! tempted to <hi>Curſe God,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Job</hi> 2.9.</note> and die!</hi> Oh my Temptations are wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, and wicked! brutiſh, and blaſphemous! horrid, and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did! Well, art tempted? yet loved. Chriſt loveth under Temptation, as well as out of Temptation.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.18.</note> 
                  <hi>For, in that he himſelf hath ſuffered being temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he is able to ſuccour them that are tempted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:33854:33"/>Art reproached? yet loved.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Oh ſay the Soul! I am under reproach, and made the Song of the Drunkard! Oh, I am under great Reproaches,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 35.11.</note> 
                  <hi>and they lay to my charge, things that I know not.</hi> Well, art reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? yet loved.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed are ye when Men ſhall revile you, and ſpeak all manner of evil againſt you, falſty for my ſake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Art perſecuted?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> yet loved. Oh ſay the Soul, I am perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted!
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Saul is in the purſuit of Me, and he hunts after my Soul to take it!</hi> Well, art perſecuted? yet loved. <hi>Perſecuted,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.9.</note> but not forſaken; caſt down, but not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Art diſpoſſeſſed? yet loved.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Oh ſay the Soul, I am poor! my barrel is empty! My Cruſe empty! I have nothing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doors! nothing within doors! I live in a Cottage! live upon
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:33854:34"/>a Common! and have ſhort Commons! Oh, I am crying concerning Bread, as <hi>Rachel</hi> cryed concerning Children? <hi>Children,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 30.1.</note> or I dye!</hi> So, Bread, or I die! Well, art diſpoſſeſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor</hi> 6.10.</note> yet loved. <hi>As having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thine, and yet poſſeſſing all things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Art unbelieving?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> yet loved. Oh ſay the Soul, though I am not an Unbeliever, yet I am unbelieving! Oh, ſay the Soul, my Faith is weak, and at low ebb? Oh my Fear, ſeems to take the wall of my Faith, and Chriſt may ſay to me, as he did to them:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.30.</note> 
                  <hi>O thou of little Faith!</hi> Well, art unbelieving? yet loved.
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.13.</note> 
                  <hi>If we believe not, yet he abideth faithful, he cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Art hated?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> yet loved. Oh ſay the Soul,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cro.</hi> 18.7.</note> 
                  <hi>I am hated! hated by the World! hated by Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours! hated by Relations!</hi> Oh
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:33854:34"/>ſay the Soul, I am hated! hated by theſe! and one ſaith con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Me, as the falſe King, ſaid concerning the true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet! There is yet one Man, by whom we may enquire of the Lord, the ſame is <hi>Mecajah,</hi> but I hate him. Well, art hated? yet loved. It is thus with Thee? ſo it is with Me: Art hated by Man? yet loved by God-Man. <hi>Ye ſhall be hated of all Nations,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mark</hi> 13.13.</note> for my names ſake: but he that endureth to the end, the ſame ſhall be ſaved</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Art hardned? yet loved.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Oh ſay the Soul, my Heart is hard! very hard! exceedingly hard! unexpreſſively hard! Oh ſay the Soul, as mine Eye is like a Pumice, ſo my Heart is like an Adamant! Oh my Heart, is hard as a Stone! hard, as an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damant-ſtone, concerning which they ſay, that nothing but Goats
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:33854:35"/>blood will ſoften it! Oh, my Heart is hard! hard as a ſtone! hard as a Mil-ſtone! <hi>hard as a piece of the nether milſtone!</hi> Well, art hardned? yet loved. <hi>I will take away thy ſtony Heart out of your Fleſh, and will give you a Heart of Fleſh.</hi> I, that <hi>(can)</hi> do it, <hi>(will)</hi> do it.</p>
               <p>Art diſtreſſed?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> yet loved. Oh ſay the Soul, as my weakneſſes are many, ſo my wants are many! My Corruption is ſtrong, but my Grace is weak; my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief ſtrong, but my Faith weak; my pride ſtrong, but my Humility weak; my Paſſion ſtrong, but my Patience weak. Oh ſay the Soul, though I do not want Grace, yet I am want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Grace! though I am not without Grace (Glory to the God of Grace, for the Grace of God) yet I have but a little Grace! Oh Sir, I am wanting
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:33854:35"/>in Grace! wanting in every Grace! Oh Sir! may not I ſay concerning any Grace? yea I do ſay concerning every Grace, as the great Doctor of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles ſaith, concerning the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Faith: <hi>Night, and Day,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.10.</note> praying exceedingly, that we might ſee your Face, and might perfect that which is lacking in your Faith.</hi> Well, art diſtreſſed? yet loved: art wanting in Grace? in every Grace? yet loved. <hi>My God ſhall ſupply all your need,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.19</note> according to his riches in glory, by Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Art diſſerted? yet loved.
<note place="margin">Laſtly.</note> Oh ſay the Soul, 'tis Night with Me! I am in the dark! yea, walking in darkneſs, and have no light! Oh, there's a cloud interpoſing between my Soul, and my Saviour! The Face of God is eclipſed, and he ſeems to cover my Soul with a cloud
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:33854:36"/>in his anger! Oh ſay the Soul, as it is ſaid,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nic.</hi> 3 6.</note> 
                  <hi>the Sun ſhall go down over the Prophets;</hi> ſo the Sun of righteouſneſs is gone done upon my Soul! Oh Sir, <hi>the Lord hath forſaken me,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.14.</note> and my God hath forgotten me!</hi> Oh, I am not (only) out of the (hand) of God, but (alſo) out of the heart of God! Oh, I am not (forſaken) only, but (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten alſo! Well, Soul art diſſerted,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.7.</note> yet loved. <hi>For a ſmal Moment have I forſaken Thee, but with great Mercies will I gather Thee.</hi> Beloved! Diſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is the loweſt Dreg of a Believers Cup: All the Hell that he ſhall have, he hath here; he ſhall have Heaven, but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Heaven hereafter.</p>
               <p>Thus Soul, ballance Chriſts Love, againſt all thy SOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ROWS, under all thy SO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LITUDES.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:33854:36"/>But, as I did begin, ſo I muſt end; and where I did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, there I ſhall end. If Chriſt hath a peculiar People, and a peculiar Love, for this pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar People, ſuffer (then) the words of Exhortation, and hold faſt this Truth, this Text, <hi>Who loved us.</hi> Let the World go, and Sin go; let Self go, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan go: But let not this Text go; this Truth go; <hi>Who loved us.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>Who loved us, and waſhed us, from our Sins, in his own Blood.</q>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:33854:37"/>
                  <head>And waſhed us from our Sins, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> his own Blood.</head>
                  <p>THat Chriſt <hi>Loving</hi> his,
<note place="margin">Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> out of Love <hi>waſheth</hi> his, and that from their <hi>Sins,</hi> in his own <hi>Blood.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved! If the Maſter of the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, pleaſe to influence a methodical Diſcourſe to Edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, ſuffer (then) an innocent Inquiry after theſe ſix things.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. What this waſhing is, that is, by Chriſts own Blood.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. What this Sins is, that is waſhed from, in Chriſts own Blood.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Whether Chriſt waſheth from Sin, in his own Blood.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. How Chriſt waſheth from Sin, in his own Blood.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Why Chriſt waſheth from Sin, in his own Blood.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:33854:37"/>6. What uſe may be made of this, that Chriſt waſheth from Sin, in his own Blood.</p>
                  <p>What this waſhing is, that is,
<note place="margin">Method.</note> by Chriſts own Blood.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                  </p>
                  <p>To this Negatively, and then Poſitively.</p>
                  <p>What this waſhing is not;
<note n="1" place="margin">Negati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vely.</note> to this generaly, and then parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly.</p>
                  <p>To waſh, is to purge,
<note n="1" place="margin">General<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note> and make clean. Thus, the Fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were gone out of their Ships, waſhing their Nets.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 5.2.</note> That is, making clean their Nets; for Nets by waſhing, are made clean; but thus you are not to underſtand it here.</p>
                  <p>There's a Natural waſhing.
<note n="2" place="margin">Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly.</note>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> There's a waſhing of the hands, and feet; a waſhing of the Body, and Cloathes for the Body. Thus (<hi>Matth.</hi> 15.20) <hi>To eat with unwaſhed hands, defileth not a Man.</hi> But thus you are not
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:33854:38"/>to underſtand it here, in the Text, <hi>And waſhed us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There's a Moral waſhing,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Thus (<hi>Pſa.</hi> 26.6.) <hi>I will waſh my hands in Innocency, ſo will I compaſs thine Altar., Jehovah,</hi> But, thus, you are not to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it here; <hi>And waſhed us</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There's a Ceremonial waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thus (<hi>Heb.</hi> 9.10.) <hi>Which ſtood only in Meats and Drinks and divers waſhings,</hi> until the time of Reformation. But, thus, you are not to underſtand it here; <hi>And waſhed us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There's a ſuperſtitious waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Thus (<hi>Matth</hi> 15.2.) <hi>Why do thy Diſciples tranſgreſs the Traditions of the Elders: for they waſh their Hands, when they eat Bread?</hi> But thus, you are not to underſtand it here; <hi>And waſhed us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There's a Miraculous waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Thus (<hi>John</hi> 9.11) Go,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:33854:38"/>and waſh; <hi>and I went, and waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and I received ſight.</hi> But, thus, you are not to underſtand it here; <hi>And waſhed us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There's a Spiritual waſhing.
<note n="2" place="margin">Poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vely.</note> There's a waſhing from the Guilt of Sin; and from the Filth of Sin: There's a Deliverance from a Conſcience of Sin, and from a Converſation of Sin: There's a waſhing Sin from off the Soul, and ſo juſtifying it; and a waſhing the Soul from off Sin, and ſo ſanctifying it. To theſe diſtinctly.</p>
                  <p>To waſh, is to juſtifie.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> To waſh, is to redeem, and reſtore, Thus (<hi>Revel.</hi> 5 9.) <hi>Thou art worthy to take the Book, and open the Seals thereof;</hi> why? <hi>for thou waſt ſlain, and haſt redeemed us to God by thy Blood, out of every kindred, and tongue, and people, and nation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To waſh, is to Sanctifie.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> As
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:33854:39"/>to waſh, is to redeem, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore, ſo, to regenerate, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new; As, to pardon, ſo to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie; As, to deliver from the Guilt, ſo, from the Filth of Sin, Thus (<hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5.) <hi>Not by works of righteouſneſs which we have done, but according to his mercy he ſaved us, by the waſhing of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, and renewing of the holy Spirit.</hi> But, both theſe (juſtifying, and Sanctifying) you have connected, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11.) <hi>And ſuch were ſome of you: but ye are waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but ye are ſanctified, but ye are juſtified, in the name of the Lord Jeſus, and by the Spirit of our God.</hi> Now, thus, (if I mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take not) you are to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it in the Text, <hi>who waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us;</hi> that is, who juſtified us from the Guilt, and ſanctified us from the Filth of our Sins, in his own Blood. <hi>And waſhed
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:33854:39"/>us from our Sins, in his own Blood.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>What this Sin is,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> that is waſhed from, in Chriſts own Blood. Sin, in the Nature, and Motion of it, is a Tranſgreſſion of the Law. Sin, ſuppoſeth a Law in being;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.15.</note> 
                     <hi>For where there is no Law, there is no Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion:</hi> But, where there is Sin, there is a Law, and a Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of that Law.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 3.4.</note> 
                     <hi>Whoſoever committeth ſin, tranſgreſſeth the Law; for ſin is a Tranſgreſſion of the Law.</hi> Yea, Sin is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Tranſgreſſion of a Law, but of a good Law;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.12.</note> 
                     <hi>For the Law is holy, and the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment holy, and juſt, and good.</hi> Yea, the Tranſgreſſion not only of a good Law, but of Gods Law.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſa.</hi> 89.30, 31.</note> 
                     <hi>If his Children forſake (my) Law, and walk not in (my) Commandements; If they break (my) Statutes, and keep not (my)
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:33854:40"/>Commandements.</hi> Now, the Law, not (only) forbids the doing of evil (whether in thought, word, or deed) but (alſo) commands the doing of Good; ſo that to omit the Good commanded, as well as to commit the Sin for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden, is Sin: whatever, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, doth tranſgreſs the Law of God (in whole, or in part) is Sin; whether it break an Affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative, or a Negative precept; that is, whether it be the Omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Good, or the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Evil. From this; all this, Chriſts blood waſheth; <hi>And waſhed us from our Sins, in his own Blood.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Whether Chriſt waſheth from Sin,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> in his own Blood. As it is true, none in Heaven, nor on Earth, nor under the Earth, could open the Book, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looſe the ſeven Seals thereof; it is as true, none in Heaven,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:33854:40"/>nor on Earth, nor under the Earth, can juſtify a guilty Soul, and ſanctifie a filthy Soul, but Chriſt; unto this my text ſpeaks, <hi>Who loved us, and waſhed us, from our Sins, in his own Blood.
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eze.</hi> 16.9.</note> Then waſhed I thee with water; yea, I throughly waſhed away thy Blood from thee;</hi> thy Bloods from thee, according to the Margent. Then; when? when I paſſed by thee.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eze.</hi> 16 6.</note> 
                     <hi>When I paſſed by thee, and ſaw thee polluted</hi> (or troden under foot) <hi>in thine own Blood. I ſaid unto thee. Live; Yea, when thou waſt in thy blood, I ſaid unto thee, Live.</hi> But what (I) is this? This <hi>Jehovah</hi> God. <hi>Thus ſaith.</hi> Jehovah,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eze.</hi> 16.3.</note> 
                     <hi>God unto Jeruſalem &amp;c.</hi> Now this <hi>Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah,</hi> is God; or Chriſt; for the Son hath the ſame name with the Father;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.6.</note> 
                     <hi>This is the name whereby he ſhall be called,</hi> Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah <hi>our Righteouſneſs</hi> 'Tis Chriſt
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:33854:41"/>that waſheth.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eze.</hi> 36.25 26, 27.</note> 
                     <hi>I will ſprinkle clean water upon you, and ye ſhall be clean; from all your filthineſs, and from all your Idols will I cleanſe you. A new heart, will I give you, and a new Spirit will I put within you, and I will take away the ſtony heart out of your fleſh, and I will give you an heart of fleſh. And I will put my Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit within you, and cauſe you to walk in my Statutes, and ye ſhall keep my Judgements, and do them.</hi> But, in ſhort; If to waſh, be to juſtifie, then Souls are waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Chriſts own Blood.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.24.</note> 
                     <hi>Being juſtified freely by his grace;</hi> but how? <hi>through the Redemption that is in Chriſt Jeſus</hi> And, if to waſh, be to ſanctifie, then Souls are waſhed in Chriſts own Blood.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>b</hi> 13.12</note> Chriſt, <hi>that he might ſanctifie the People with his own blood, ſuffered without the Gate.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> How Chriſt waſheth from
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:33854:41"/>Sin, in his own Blood.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt waſheth three wayes: by his Word; by his Spirit; and by his Blood.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By his Word.</hi> Chriſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and approved his word, as a means leading unto this end.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jo.</hi> 17.17.</note> 
                     <hi>Sanctifie them through thy Truth, thy word is Truth.</hi> As to waſh, is to juſtifie, ſo to ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie; Now, though the word can do nothing without Chriſt, no more then the Inſtrument can without the hand; yet, this Inſtrument, together with the hand, can juſtifie a condemned Creature, and ſanctifie a cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated Creature.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By his Spirit</hi> The word,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> that's as the wax; the Spirit, that's as the Seal upon that wax. The Spirit (indeed) is the principal verb in the Sentence; Sanctification (properly) is the work of the Spirit; For, as it is
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:33854:42"/>the proper work of the F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ther to elect; and, of the Son to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem; ſo of the Spirit to ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie thoſe Elected, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed. 'Tis, therefore, called the Sanctification of the Spirit. <hi>Ye are choſen unto Salvation,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.13.</note> through Sanctification of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By his Blood.</hi>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> As Chriſt waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth through his <hi>Word;</hi> and through his <hi>Spirit;</hi> ſo through his <hi>Blood.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But how may Chriſt be ſaid,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion. </seg>
                     </label> to waſh from Sin, in his own Blood?</p>
                  <p>There is a <hi>virtual,</hi>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Solut. </seg>
                     </label> and an <hi>actual</hi> waſhing, in Chriſts blood. That is, there is a Satis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>action given to God (for) Man; and a ſanctification wrought (in) Man.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Virtual.</hi>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> There is a ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on given to God, Beloved! There is the Active, and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:33854:42"/>Obedience of Chriſt; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his Active, himſelf ſpeaks: <hi>I have finiſhed the work,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jo.</hi> 17.4.</note> which thou gaveſt me to do.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his Paſſive, himſelf (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo) ſpeaks: <hi>It is finiſhed.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jo.</hi> 19.30.</note> Here was the <hi>Croſs,</hi> and <hi>Crucifixtion</hi> of Chriſt, as the <hi>Complement</hi> of <hi>All.</hi> Theſe two, his <hi>Active,</hi> and <hi>Paſſive</hi> Obedience, were (joint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) and (equally) concerned, in giving Satisfaction to infinite <hi>Juſtice:</hi> Now, concerning theſe two, his Action, and Paſſion (if I miſtake not) God ſaith:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.17. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleaſed:</hi> Or, (according to the Greek) in whom I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſce. God, did acquieſce in him as Son; as Mediator of the promiſe; as one that did, and dyed, and ſo ſatisfied. Chriſt, himſelf, did not only arrive at a Satisfaction, by his <hi>Action,</hi> and <hi>Paſſion;</hi> but (if I may ſpeak
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:33854:43"/>it without Levity, and with a holy Reverence) arrived God at a Satisfaction, by his <hi>Doing</hi> and <hi>Dying,</hi> and that for <hi>All</hi> for whom he gave himſelf: and unto whom he hath given, and ſhall give himſelf. Both which (I think) are legible in that o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Prophet:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.11.</note> 
                     <hi>He ſhall ſee of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Travel of his Soul, and be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>atis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; by his knowledge, ſhall m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> righteous Servant juſtifie many for he ſhall bear their Iniquities.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Actual.</hi>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> There is a Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation wrought in Man. A there is a Satisfaction give (to) God (for) Man, ſo the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is a ſanctification wrought (by) God (in) Man. If the Blood o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Bulls, and of Goats, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> aſhes of an Heffer ſprincklin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the unclean, ſanctified to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> purifying of the fleſh:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.13, 14.</note> 
                     <hi>Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> much more ſhall the blood <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Chriſt, who through the etern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="71" facs="tcp:33854:43"/>Spirit, offered himſelf without ſpot to God, purge your conſcience from dead works, to ſerve the living God?</hi> Here's purging, and purifying; here's ſanctifying, and ſpiriting unto Service; but how? through blood; That is, through an Application of Chriſts blood; and this appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is through Faith; For the Apoſtle wordeth it;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25.</note> 
                     <hi>Whom</hi> (ſpeaking of Chriſt) <hi>God hath ſet forth</hi> (or ſo ordained) <hi>to be a propitiation</hi> (or mercy-ſeat;) but how? <hi>through Faith in the Blood.</hi> So that all arrive at a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction (with reſpect to Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, and Sanctification) concerning this Blood: Chriſt, was ſatisfied, in ſhedding his Blood; God, was ſatisfied, in Chriſts ſhedding his Blood; And Man, is ſatisfied, becauſe inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſed in this Blood that was ſhed; being delivered, not from
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:33854:44"/>a Conſcience of Sin (only), but from a Converſation of Sin (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo). <hi>And waſhed us from our Sins, in his own Blood.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Why Chriſt waſheth from Sin,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> in his own Blood. Chriſt waſheth from Sin, in a two fold Reſpect; in reſpect of the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity (of) it; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in reſpect of the commodity (by) it.
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>
                     </label>
                  </p>
                  <p>In reſpect of the Neceſſity of it.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> It is expedient that one ſhould dye for the People, and that the whole Nation periſh not. There's a Neceſſity of Chriſts Blood, and that for theſe two Reaſons, among others.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe Man had ſinned.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Man, is defiled, and therefore Man muſt be waſhed. Every man (in a ſtate of Nature) is a <hi>Bartimeus</hi> (the Son of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean) as the word ſignifieth. Oh Soul, here's thy pedigree, though an Emperor was thy
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:33854:44"/>Father, yet <hi>Adam</hi> was thy Grand-Father! To this purpoſe the Apoſtle ſpeaks: <hi>Wherefore,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom</hi> 5.12.</note> as by one Man ſin entred into the World, and Death by Sin; and ſo death paſſed upon all Men, for that all have ſinned.</hi> Or, in whom all have ſinned; ſo the Greek.
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> Every Man, and Woman, living in the Region of depraved Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is a <hi>Nero,</hi> (a Sinner) as the word ſignifie. Man, is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed, and that from Head,
<note place="margin">A Capite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad Calcew.</note> to Foot; that (as the Philoſopher ſaith, concerning the Soul, it is in every part; where there is Life, there is the Soul:
<note place="margin">Tota in to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ota in qualibet parte.</note> for the Soul is the Life; ſo, what ever is in us, and commeth from us, and is acted by us, receive a defilement from us. Sin, is like a Leproſie, over the whole man; like a Gangrene, ſpreading over the whole Soul. There is, therefore, a neceſſity
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:33854:45"/>of Chriſts Blood, in order to Pardon, and in order to Purity.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe God would be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> God, is infinite in his At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes, as well as in his Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; Juſtice, is one of Gods Attributes, and God will not looſe one of his Attributes. If Man ſin, God will avenge this ſin, upon the Perſon, or upon the Paſſover. As Man had ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſo God would be ſatisfied; yea, ſatisfied, the ſame way he was offended.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.21.</note> 
                     <hi>By Man came Death, by man came (alſo) the Reſurrection of the dead.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In reſpect of the Commodity by it.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Blood of Chriſt is advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious in a maniſold reſpect.</p>
                  <p>At this Door of Chriſts Blood,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> enters Redemption. Is not Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption a great thing? to be reſcued out of the hands of the roaring Lyon, is not this a great
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:33854:45"/>Mercy? This is through Chriſts Blood.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.7.</note> 
                     <hi>In whom we have Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption;</hi> but how? <hi>through his Blood.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>At this Door of Chriſts Blood,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> enters Remiſſion. Is not Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion a great thing? Pardon of Sin, is not (only) a ſingular, but (alſo) a plural Mercy;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.22.</note> 
                     <hi>this Remiſſion is through Chriſts blood.</hi> Without ſhedding of blood, no Remiſſion.</p>
                  <p>At this Door of Chriſts Blood,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> enters Acceſs to God. Is not Acceſs to God a great thing? Acceſs to a mortal Monarch, is eyed as a great thing; but what is Acceſs to an immortal God then? Sin, had ſet God, and Man, at an infinite diſtance, Chriſts Blood bring theſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. The Apoſtle ſpeaking of Chriſts preaching Peace, to them which were aſar off, and to them which were nigh, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joins
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:33854:46"/>joins this,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.17, 18.</note> 
                     <hi>For, through him, we both have an Acceſs by one Spirit unto the Father.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>At this Door of Chriſts Blood,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> enters Acceptance with God. There's an Acceptation through Chriſt, and his Blood, as to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and as to Performance.</p>
                  <p>There is (through Chriſts Blood) an Acceptation as to Perſon.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Man, was indebted, and the Blood of Chriſt went to pay the Reckoning.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.6.</note> 
                     <hi>Ye are bought with a price:</hi> Chriſts Blood went for pay. <hi>To the praiſe of the glory of his grace, wherein he hath made us accepted in the beloved.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is (through Chriſts Blood) an Acceptation as to Performance.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> As God hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the Perſon of an <hi>Abel,</hi> ſo to the Oblation of an <hi>Abel;</hi> but, reſpect to both, through Chriſt. Chriſt, is a <hi>merciful,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:33854:46"/>and faithful high Prieſt,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.17.</note> in things partaining to God, to make ricon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation for the Sin of the People.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>At this Door of Chriſts Blood,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> enters Salvation. Is not Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a great thing? Is not this worth the hearing? worth the having? Is not Damnation a bitter Pil? a bitter Potion? This Salvation, is through Chriſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, from <hi>Wrath,</hi> and from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> If the wrath of a King, be as the Meſſenger of death, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> what's the wrath of a God then! the wrath of the God of Gods then! Chriſt, by his blood, ſaveth from wrath.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.25.</note> 
                     <hi>Who was delivered for our offences, and raiſed again for our Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From <hi>Sin.</hi>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> As the Blood of Chriſt, ſaveth from the Guilt of Sin, ſo from the Filth of Sin. He ſhall ſave the People from
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:33854:47"/>their Sins.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.21.</note> As Chriſt is a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour (for) Sin, ſo (from) Sin.</p>
                  <p>What <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> may be made of this,
<note place="margin">Laſtly.</note> that <hi>Chriſt waſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th from Sin, in his own Blood.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here are three uſes;
<note place="margin">USE.</note> Caution; Comfort; Counſel.</p>
                  <p>Now this Uſe hath a double Aſpect,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                     <note place="margin">By way of Caution.</note> and looks unto the waſhed, and unwaſhed; Now, if ſo, there muſt be a diſtinct diſcuſſion, in a way of Caution.</p>
                  <p>Art loved?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                     <note place="margin">To the waſhed.</note> and waſhed? be cautioned (then) againſt ſinning, for Chriſts Blood muſt go for waſhing.</p>
                  <p>Beloved! what all the water in the Sea cannot do, the Blood of Chriſt can do. If thou beeſt waſhed from Sin, 'tis by Chriſts Blood. What Man in his wits, will be laviſh of his blood! Oh, what Soul, in love with Chriſt, being loved of Chriſt, will be laviſh of Chriſts Blood! Soul!
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:33854:47"/>if there be ſinning by Thee, and Mee, his Blood muſt go for waſhing. Hath not Chriſt bled enough already, when he hath bled to death, to an accurſed death, but muſt he bleed again? That, as he was pierced again, muſt he bleed again?
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jo.</hi> 20.27.</note> 
                     <hi>Come.</hi> Thomas, <hi>reach hither thy hand, and thruſt it into my ſide.</hi> I was once pierced, and wilt thou pierce me (by thy <hi>unbelief</hi>) a ſecond time? So, ſhall we bleed Chriſt again? Oh take heed of ſinning, for Chriſts Blood muſt go for waſhing! That, as it is ſaid, <hi>Take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eed to thy ſelf,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Diut.</hi> 4.9.</note> and keep thy Soul diligently.</hi> So, take heed of ſinning, for Chriſts Blood go for waſhing. Oh Soul! if thou haſt any love for thy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, love for thy Soveraign, love for thy Soul, when thou findeſt any Corruption bubling within, then let this Text ring
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:33854:48"/>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thine ears: <hi>Who loved us, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſhed us, from our Sins, in his own Blood.</hi> Oh Soul! when thou findeſt a Temptation preſented; <hi>A Snare on</hi> Mizpah,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.1.</note> 
                     <hi>and a Net ſpread upon Tabor;</hi> then ſay with Joſeph,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.9.</note> 
                     <hi>How can I do this great wickedneſs, and ſin againſt God?</hi> Did Chriſt do? and ſhall I ſin? Did Chriſt dye? and ſhall I fin? Is Chriſt waſhing? and ſhall I be ſinning? Oh who ſhould ſin, and cauſe Chriſt to pay ſo dear for it! <hi>Who loved us, and waſhed us, from our Sins, in his own Blood.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Art not waſhed?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> be caution<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (then) againſt denying the efficacy of Chriſts Blood.
<note place="margin">To the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waſhed.</note> As the <hi>Papiſts</hi> lead from the Blood of Chriſt, to the blood of <hi>Hales,</hi> and <hi>Becket;</hi> So, there is a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, of a late Edition, (Couſin-Germans to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts) who lead from the blood
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:33854:48"/>of Chriſt, to the blood in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. They ſay,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Haldo's Key, &amp;c. p.</hi> 63.</note> that the blood of Chriſt, is the Life of Chriſt; that is, the power of the light in them. They ſay, that Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Purification, and Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niliation, they are not by that Blood of Chriſt, ſhed on the Croſs, but by that blood of the Spiritual Body of fleſh, blood, and bones, which (they ſay) Chriſt deſcended in; and which (they ſay) is in every one of them, as really, as in (that) Man, who was the Son of <hi>Mary.</hi> By this (it ſeems) that Salvation is by no other blood, but what is in themſelves: But, let God be true, and every Man (in this matter) a Lyar. The Blood of Chriſt, muſt needs be effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, for 'tis called the Blood of God. <hi>Feed the Church of God,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Act.</hi> 10.28.</note> which he lead purchaſed with his own Blood.</hi> 'Tis not (then) a
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:33854:49"/>blood in themſelves, but was a blood in Himſelf, and this was the Blood which was let out, and trickled down upon the Croſs. One little Drop (ſays <hi>Luther</hi>) of Chriſts blood, is of more worth then Heaven, and Earth. What is the blood of a Grape? the blood of a Son? yea, of an only Son, to the blood of the only begotten Son of God? yea, to the blood of that Chriſt,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16.</note> who is, God <hi>mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in the fleſh?</hi> The Soul may feel; yea, the Soul muſt feel himſelf to ſtand in exceſſive need, even of the leaſt drop of Chriſts blood, for the waſhing away of his Sins. <hi>And waſhed us, from our Sins, in his own Blood.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Art loved?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> be joyous (then) thou art univerſally waſhed from thy Sins,
<note place="margin">By way of Comfert.</note> in Chriſts Blood. Chriſt ſaith to every believing
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:33854:49"/>Saint, and ſanctified Believer, as he did to <hi>Peter:</hi> He that is waſhed, needeth not one to waſh his feet, but is clean every whit; <hi>and ye are clean,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jo.</hi> 13 10.</note> but not all.</hi> Is clean every whit; is wholy, or univerſally clean,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> according to the Greek. Now, Soul, art loved? and (out of love) waſhed, and that univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally? go not (then) away with thy Countenance ſad.</p>
                  <p>Oh but (as <hi>Rebecca</hi> ſaid) I may ſay! <hi>If things be ſo,
<label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.12.</note> why am I thus?</hi> If I be univerſally waſhed, what mean thoſe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Inmates, and curſed make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates within? what mean that pride, and paſſion within? what mean that wantonneſs, &amp; world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs within? what mean that Unbelief, and Misbelief with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in? Oh Sir! if I be univerſally waſhed, what mean theſe vain, and vile Thoughts within? what
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:33854:50"/>mean thoſe hard, and high Thoughts within? what mean thoſe brutiſh, and blaſphemous Thoughts within? If things be ſo,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Solut. </seg>
                     </label> why am I thus?</p>
                  <p>A Soul, waſhed by Chriſt, may be conſidered two wayes; in his Juſtification, and in his Sanctification.</p>
                  <p>In his Juſtification.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Now, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, is formally, inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, and materially in Chriſt. Thus, a loved Soul, ſtands com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly, and perfectly waſhed, in Chriſts own blood. Thus, a loved Soul, is compared unto the Sun, which is without ſpots. <hi>Thou art all fair,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.7.</note> my Love, and there is no ſpot in thee.</hi> Thus, a loved Soul, is preſented (by Chriſt) without ſpot, or wrinkle, or any ſuch thing; For this is the Doctrine which the Apoſtle preacheth,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.25.</note> and (I bleſſe God) that I do believe what he preach.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:33854:50"/>In his Sanctification. Thus,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> a loved Soul is black.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.5.</note> 
                     <hi>I am black, but comely, oh Daughters of Jeruſalem!</hi> Comely, as to Juſtification; black, as to San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification. Look not upon me, becauſe <hi>I am black;
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.6.</note> becauſe the Sun hath looked upon me.</hi> A loved Soul, is compared to the Sun (which is without ſpots) as to his Juſtification; but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Moon (which is full of Spots) as to his Sanctification.</p>
                  <p>Oh, but I cannot believe,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> that I am waſhed from all Sin! Though I may be waſhed from the Sin of my youth, yet not from the Sin of my old age: Oh, though I may be waſhed from open Sins, yet not from ſecret Sins! Oh, though I am not ſo profane as I was! and ſo polluted as I was! yet, this I find, that when I would do good, evil is preſent with! Oh,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:33854:51"/>this lay near my heart!
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.19.21.</note> 
                     <hi>The good I would do, I do not; but the evil that I would not do, that do I!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Canſt not believe an univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal waſhing?
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Solut. </seg>1</label> know, that the Author of Faith, is the Actor of Faith.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2.</note> 
                     <hi>Looking unto Jeſus, the Author, and Finiſher of our Faith.</hi> Here, Faith, being a principal grace, is Synecdochically put for all Grace. Chriſt, muſt not only work Faith, but ſet Faith a work, or thou wilt not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve an univerſal waſhing.</p>
                  <p>When thou wouldeſt do good,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> is evil preſent with thee! So, it is with Me. May not I ſay, with a holy Reverence, as Chriſt did to the Scribes, and Phariſees?
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.7.</note> 
                     <hi>He that is without Sin among you, let him firſt caſt a ſtone at her.</hi> So, that Perſon, that do not find evil preſent with him, when he would do
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:33854:51"/>good, let him firſt caſt a ſtone at Me; and at Thee.</p>
                  <p>Thou art univerſally waſhed,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> if loved, though thou doſt not believe it. If waſhed from one Sin, waſhed from all Sins; that is, thou art <hi>(waſhed)</hi> from all Sin, in point of Juſtification; and thou art <hi>(waſhing)</hi> from all Sin, in point of Sanctification. Chriſts blood, extend, to the waſhing away of all Sin.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 1.7.</note> 
                     <hi>If we walk in the light, as he is in the light, we have Fellowſhip one with another, and the blood of Jeſus Chriſt his Son, cleanſeth us from all Sins.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Oh, but,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>3</label> though there be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence now, there may be Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fring ere long! Though there he ſilence here, there's ſuffering elſe where! Oh, though there be peace now, there may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware ere long! Though there be proſperity now, there may
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:33854:52"/>be adverſity ere long! Oh, though it be Summer now, it may be Winter ere long!</p>
                  <p>Though the Woman be in the Wilderneſs,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution. </seg>
                     </label> yet ſhe ſhall come out,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.5.</note> 
                     <hi>leaning upon her Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved.</hi> Soul, art loved? though thou beeſt, or ſhouldeſt be in Tribulation; yea, in great Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation, yet thou mayeſt come out of that great Tribulation. <hi>Theſe are they that came out of great Tribulation,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.14.</note> having waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Robes, and made them white in the blood of the Lamb.</hi> Now, wilt thou, that art loved, and univerſally waſhed, from thy Sins in Chriſts own blood, go away with thy countenance ſad? Oh Soul! pluck a Cluſter from this <hi>Vine;</hi> and take a Drop from this honey-comb: <hi>Who loved us, and waſhed us, from our Sins, in his own Blood.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Doth Chriſt waſh from Sin,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
                     <pb n="89" facs="tcp:33854:52"/>in his own Blood?
<note place="margin">By way of Counſel.</note> Suffer (then) the words of Exhortation.</p>
                  <p>Now, here, I would ſpeak to the unwaſhed, and the waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
                  <p>Art not waſhed?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Go (then) to Chriſt for waſhing.
<note place="margin">To the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waſhed.</note> No more, ſhall have a Crown, then have a Chriſt; ſhall have Glory, then have Grace; and ſhall have Happineſs, then have Holineſs. If, therefore, thou wouldeſt be juſtified before God, and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified before Man, go to Chriſt. <hi>If I waſh thee not,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jo.</hi> 13 8.</note> (and 'tis Chriſt that ſpeaks it) <hi>thou haſt no part with Me.</hi> Whether, would ye go? whether ſhould ye go? whether, will ye go? whether, can ye go, but unto Chriſt, who loveth, and waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from Sin, in his own Blood? Art unwaſhed? go (then) to Chriſt for waſhing.</p>
                  <p>But, is it Chriſts will,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion </seg>1</label> as well
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:33854:53"/>us Chriſts work, that I ſhould go to him, to be waſhed?</p>
                  <p>As it is Chriſts work to waſh,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
                     </label> ſo, it is Chriſts will that thou ſhouldeſt be waſhed.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.7.</note> 
                     <hi>This is the will of God, even your ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification.</hi> Now, God, and Chriſt will, and nill, the ſame things.</p>
                  <p>But may thoſe that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waſhed,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>2</label> go to Chriſt to be waſhed.</p>
                  <p>As unto whom,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
                     </label> ſhould an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waſhed Soul go, but unto Chriſt; So, none but unclean Souls (Souls ſenſible of their <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers,</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs</hi>) will go to Chriſt to be waſhed.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat</hi> 9.12.</note> 
                     <hi>The whole need no Phyſitian</hi> (that is, ſee no need of a Phyſician) <hi>but thoſe that are ſick,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But did ever a Soul,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>3</label> ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean as I, go to Chriſt to be waſhed? Oh! I am a <hi>Gehazi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> he was no fuller of Leproſie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:33854:53"/>then I am of Sin; and yet he went out of his Maſters pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, a Leper as white as Snow.</p>
                  <p>A Sinner thou art,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
                     </label> and no more thou art; now, though a Sinner be a Subject of miſery, yet an object of Mercy.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.</note> 
                     <hi>The Son of Man is come to ſeek, and to ſave, that which was loſt.</hi>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>4</label> If I muſt go to Chriſt, to be waſhed in his Blood, then, what manner of Blood, is Chriſts Blood.</p>
                  <p>Beloved! My Line,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
                     </label> will not ſound this Bottom, for it is a bottomleſs Bottom; but I will let it down, for Chriſt can make a Feaſt of a Fragment. Take a Taſt, though but a Taſt.</p>
                  <p>Chriſts Blood,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> is a Heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoftning blood. The heart of Man is ſtony; yea, like an Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant ſtone, concerning which ſtone, they ſay, that nothing
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:33854:54"/>but Goats-blood will ſoften it. Oh Soul, though thy heart be like an Adamant-ſtone; <hi>yea, like the nether Milſtone,</hi> yet the blood of Chriſt can ſoften it. <hi>I will take away the ſtony heart out of their fleſh,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eze.</hi> 11.19.</note> and will give them a heart of fleſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Chriſts Blood,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> is a juſtifying blood. Juſtification, is a great thing, and a gracious thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; to be acquitted from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> and Death, and accounted righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous unto Life, and Glory; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o not this great? greatly great? This, is through Chriſts blood. <hi>That being juſtified by his blood,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.9.</note> we ſhould be ſaved from wrath through him</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Chriſts Blood;
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> is a Sin-mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying blood. Beloved! ye muſt look upon your Sin, as that which was the death of your Lord; and ye muſt look upon the death of your Lord, as that
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:33854:54"/>which is the death of your Sin. <hi>Our old Man is crucified with him,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.6.</note> that the body of Sin may be deſtroyed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Chriſts Blood,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> is purchaſing blood. There was little paid for the Saviour, they ſold him for thirty pieces of Silver, but there was much paid for the Sinner. <hi>Ye are not redeemed with corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table things;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18, 19.</note> there's the Negative part; but what are theſe? Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and Gold: But, if Silver; and Gold cannot, what can? the blood of Chriſt can: but, with the precious blood of Chriſt. <hi>Ye are not redeemed with corruptable things, as Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and Gold, but with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious blood of Chriſt.</hi> The blood of Chriſt, is the price of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
                  <p>Chriſts Blood,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> is pardoning blood. Oh what weariſome days, and nights, have many
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:33854:55"/>Souls! but what's the reaſon? they want a pardon. Do not theſe ſay at night, oh that it were morning? And, in the morning, oh that it were night! Oh how can you reſt day, or night, that are without a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don! Chriſts blood, is pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing blood.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Col.</hi> 1.14.</note> 
                     <hi>In whom we have Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption through his blood,</hi> the forgiveneſs of Sins.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt Blood,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> is pleading blood. <hi>Abels</hi> blood, did plead againſt the Offender, but Chriſts blood plead for the Believer. <hi>Abels</hi> blood, did cry for ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.24</note> but Chriſts blood cry for Mercy. 'Tis called the blood of ſprinkling, that ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth better things then that of <hi>Abel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Chriſts Blood,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> is a pacifying blood. Chriſts blood, is the blood of <hi>Atonement.</hi> No ſooner was <hi>Haman</hi> executed, but <hi>Aha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuerus</hi>
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:33854:55"/>was appeaſed. No ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er was Chriſt crucified, but God was pacified. And you,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Col.</hi> 1.21, 22.</note> that were ſometimes alienated, and enemies in your minds by wicked works, yet now hath he reconciled; but how? in the body of the fleſh through death.</p>
                  <p>Chriſts Blood,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> is a procuring blood. Our Sins, did ſhut Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens gate, but the blood of Chriſt is the Key, that open the gate of Paradiſe for us. 'Tis Chriſt that hath the Key of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> opening, and no man ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; ſhutting, and no man o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening Loved ones have bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to enter into the holieſt;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.19.</note> but how? by the blood of <hi>Jeſus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Chriſts Blood, is pure blood.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Beloved! we have our <hi>Blots,</hi> in our <hi>Scutcheons;</hi> our <hi>Weeds,</hi> in our <hi>Gardent;</hi> our <hi>Rubbiſh,</hi> in our <hi>Houſes;</hi> our <hi>Leaven,</hi> in our <hi>Hearts;</hi> our <hi>Holes,</hi> in our <hi>Coats;</hi>
                     <pb n="96" facs="tcp:33854:56"/>but Chriſt, had none in <hi>His.</hi> Impure blood, run in our veins; but only pure blood run in <hi>His.</hi> He,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.15.</note> was in all points tempted, like as we are, yet without Sin.</p>
                  <p>Chriſts Blood,
<note place="margin">Laſtly.</note> is purifying blood. As the blood of Chriſt, is a blood of <hi>value,</hi> and of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit;</hi> ſo, 'tis a blood of <hi>Vertue,</hi> and <hi>Spirit.</hi> This blood is a Laver, to waſh in; it waſheth a <hi>Crimſon Sinner,</hi> Milk-white. Now, this is (if I miſtake not) a part of the waſhing in the Text: <hi>And waſhed us, form our Sins, in his own Blood.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Doth Chriſt waſh from Sin,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                     <note place="margin">To the waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> in his own Blood? ſenſe (then) thy Heart, with the <hi>Nature</hi> of Sin. Sin, defileth the Soul, and Chriſts <hi>Blood</hi> muſt go to waſh it. Sin, makes man a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>Black,</hi> and 'tis Chriſts <hi>Blood</hi> muſt make him perfectly <hi>White.
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.15.</note> 
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the pure, all things
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:33854:56"/>are pure, but unto them that are defiled, and unbelieving is nothing pure, but even their Mind, and Cinſcience is defiled</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Doth Chriſts Blood waſh from Sin? Take (then) a view here of mans inſufficiency to waſh himſelf.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.23.</note> 
                     <hi>Can the Ethio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian change his skin? or the Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard his ſpots?</hi> Man; any man, muſt live in his ulcers; lye in his ulcers; dye in his ulcers, and be damned for his ulcers, if Chriſt (in his own Blood) waſh him not from his ulcers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Doth Chriſts Blood waſh from Sin? pray (then) for the Blood of ſprinkling upon all thy Sacrifices, and Service. It was the ſaying of (One) <q>Oh truſt not in Man that ſhall dye,
<note place="margin">Earl of Strafford.</note> nor in the Son of Man, that ſhall be made as Graſs! There's no Confidence in Princes; the only thing that
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:33854:57"/>ſtands by a man is the Blood of Chriſt, and the Teſtimony of a good Conſcience.</q> And, I have read of another,
<note place="margin">Mr. Herbert</note> whoſe ſaying was (when he heard any of his good works mentioned) Ah! it is a good work, if it be waſhed in the Blood of Chriſt.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2.</note> Of this blood, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaks; And ſprinkling of the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Doth Chriſts Blood waſh from Sin? wonder (then) the Riches of free-Grace. Waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is but an effect, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent of Loving. Here's lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and then waſhing; yea, waſhing from Sin; from all Sin, and that in Blood; yea, in Chriſts own Blood. <hi>Who loved Me, and gave himſelf for Me.</hi> That is,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20.</note> 
                     <hi>who loved Me, and</hi> (out of love) <hi>gave himſelf to Death for Me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Doth Chriſt waſh from Sin,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> in
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:33854:57"/>his own Blood? Improve (then) this Text, and Truth, as an <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidote</hi> to expel Poyſon. May not this Text ſerve, and be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved as a Counter-poyſon? <hi>And waſhed us, from our Sins, in his own Blood.</hi> May not this Text, and Truth, be improved, as an Electuary for the Soul? <hi>And waſhed us, from our Sins, in his own Blood.</hi> For inſtance</p>
                  <p>Art tempted? yet waſhed.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Oh ſay the Soul, I am tempted! dayly tempted! greatly temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted! tempted to curſe God, and die! (<hi>Job</hi> 2.9) Art temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? yet waſhed; here's an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidote for this poyſon; <hi>And waſhed us, from our Sins, in his own Blood.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Art troubled? yet waſhed.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Oh, ſay the Soul, I ſee all things come alike to all! There's no new thing under the Sun. Oh, I am troubled! troubled on e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:33854:58"/>ſide; and my Troubles come like waves (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.8.) Art troubled? yet waſhed; <hi>And waſhed us, from our Sins, in his own Blood.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Art reproached?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> yet waſhed. Oh, ſay the Soul, I ſuffer much in my name; and am accounted an <hi>Achan,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cro.</hi> 2.7.</note> the Troubler of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael!</hi> Art reproached? yet waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>And waſhed us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Art hardned?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> yet waſhed. Oh, ſay the Soul, my heart is like an Adamant, harder then a Flint! (<hi>Ezech.</hi> 3.9.) Art hardned? yet waſhed. <hi>And waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Art hated?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> yet waſhed. Oh, ſay the Soul, I am hated! hated of Relations! It may be ſaid of them, concerning me, as was of <hi>Ammon,</hi> concerning <hi>Tamar</hi> (2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.15.) That the hatred, where with they hate me, is greater then the love
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:33854:58"/>where with they have loved Me. Art hated? yet waſhed <hi>And waſhed us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Art poor? yet waſhed. Oh,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> ſay the Soul, I am poor! I am like the poor Widow (<hi>Mark</hi> 12.42.) that had her two Mites, which made but a Farthing? Art poor? yet waſhed. <hi>And waſhed us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Art perſecuted? yet waſhed.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Oh, ſay the Soul, <hi>I am hunted! hunted as a Partridge in the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains!</hi> (1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26 20.) Art per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted? yet waſhed. <hi>And waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Art unbelieving? yet waſhed.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Oh, ſay the Soul, my Faith is at a low Ebb, and like the Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Son (<hi>Jo.</hi> 4, 47.) at the point of death! Art unbelieving? yet waſhed. <hi>And waſhed us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Art weak? yet waſhed. Oh,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> ſay the Soul, I am weak! the outward man weakens dayly!
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:33854:59"/>weakens greatly! Oh, I may ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>the time of my departure is at hand!</hi> (2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.6.) Art weak? yet waſhed. <hi>And waſhed us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Art diſſerted?
<note place="margin">Laſtly.</note> yet waſhed. Oh, ſay the Soul, 'tis Night now! Midnight now! Oh, the Face of God is hid now! not a ſmile, and a ſhine now! not a glimps, and a glaunce now! Oh, I may ſay, as the Pſalmiſt doth (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.7.) <hi>thou didſt hide thy Facc, and I was troubled!</hi> Art diſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? yet waſhed; <hi>And waſhed us.</hi> May not (now) this Text, and Truth, be improved as an Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote? Chriſt loving his, waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his; yea, out of love to his, waſheth his, and that from Sin, in his own Blood.</p>
                  <q>Who loved us, and waſhed us, from our Sins, in his own Blood.</q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:33854:59"/>
               <head>THE Churches Stock, OR, Believers Patrimony.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Gal. 3.16. (former part.)</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <q>But to Abraham, and his Seed, were the promiſes made.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>IF there be a Context, I ſhall humbly take leave of that. In the Text, you have the Perſons, and the Predicate.</p>
               <p>The Perſons: <hi>Abraham,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and his Seed.</hi> His Seed; what Seed? His Believing Seed; his Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Seed; his Seed by the free-Woman. And, that this is the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:33854:60"/>Seed, you may run, and read, in the words following the Text: <hi>He ſaith not, And to Seeds, as of many, but as of one; and to thy Seed, which is Chriſt.</hi> Not <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> and <hi>Iſaac;</hi> but <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and not <hi>Iſhmael:</hi> Not <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Jacob;</hi> but <hi>Jacob,</hi> and not <hi>Eſau:</hi> not thoſe born after the Fleſh, but thoſe born after the Spirit. <hi>And to thy Seed,</hi> which is Chriſt; of whom <hi>Iſaac</hi> was a lively, and a lovely Type. <hi>To Abraham, and his Seed; And to thy Seed, which is Chriſt.</hi> Now, in that compleat Genealogy of Chriſt <hi>(Luke the third)</hi> you have (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other things) this,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 3 34.</note> who was the Son of <hi>Abraham. And to thy Seed,</hi> which is Chriſt; that is, Chriſt, and all that are Chriſts; Chriſt, and all that are choſen, and called, in, and by Chriſt, both Jews and Gentiles. And, that this is (thee) Seed of
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:33854:60"/>
                  <hi>Abraham</hi> (who is ſtiled the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Faithful) is evidently evident, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. from the <hi>ſixth</hi> to the <hi>fourterth Verſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Predicate.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> That which is ſpoken, concerning theſe, is, that the promiſes were made unto theſe: <hi>To Abraham, and his Seed, were the promiſes made.</hi> The Perſons, are Believers, and the Promiſes are their Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony Now, <hi>to Abraham, and his Seed were the promiſes made.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That thoſe; all thoſe;
<note place="margin">Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> and only thoſe, who are Goſpel-Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, have a Goſpel-right, to Goſpel-promiſes.</p>
               <p>That <hi>Abraham</hi> was a Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, who doubts? And, that (this) Seed, which are called (his) Seed, are Believers, none need to doubt, by what (I think) I have already written. So that what I have made the matter of my Meditation, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:33854:61"/>as the Doctrinal-Truth, doth (without ſtraining) ariſe out of the Text. That Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers, have a Goſpel-right, to Goſpel promiſes.</p>
               <p>In the proſecution of this propoſition, ſuffer an innocent inquiry after theſe ſix things.</p>
               <p>What theſe Goſpel-Believers are,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Method.</hi> 1.</note> that have a Goſpel-right to promiſes.</p>
               <p>What theſe promiſes are,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which Goſpel-Believers have a Goſpel-right.</p>
               <p>Whether Goſpel.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Believers, have a Goſpel-right, to Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>promiſes.</p>
               <p>How,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Goſpel-Believers, have a Goſpel-right, to Goſpel-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</p>
               <p>Why,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Goſpel-Believers, have a Goſpel-right, to Goſpel-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</p>
               <p>What uſe may be made of this,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> That Goſpel-Believers,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:33854:61"/>have a Goſpel-right, to Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>promiſes.</p>
               <p>What theſe Goſpel-Believers are,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> that have a Goſpel-right to promiſes.</p>
               <p>I would hope to arrive thee at a Diſcovery of a Goſpel-Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever, under a Diſcuſſion of a Goſpel-Faith. There is the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit of Faith, and the Act of Faith.</p>
               <p>There's the Habit of Faith.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> There's the Seed of Faith, or Faith in the Seed. The Heart, that's the Soil, and Grace, that's the Seed. <hi>Being born again,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Petr.</hi> 1.23.</note> not of corruptible ſeed, but of incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible.</hi> Grace, is the Seed; Faith, is (a) Grace, if no (thee) Grace, for 'tis the leading Grace; the Grace that lead the <hi>Van</hi> of all other Graces. Grace, is the Seed, and this is incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible. As there is no Grace in Sin, ſo, there is no Sin in Grace.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:33854:62"/>There's the Act of Faith.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> As there is the Habit of Faith, ſo there is the Act of Faith.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.6.</note> As there is the work of Faith, ſo there is a working-Faith. <hi>But Faith, which worketh by Love.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what manner of Faith,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion. </seg>
                  </label> is this Faith?</p>
               <p>'Tis a Faith that hath Chriſt for Object.
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Solut. </seg>1</label> That (He) might be juſt,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom</hi> 3.26.</note> and the juſtifier of him that believeth in (Jeſus.) This Faith, hath Chriſt (but not the lying viſion of the heart) for its Object.</p>
               <p>'Tis a Faith of the Operation of God.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Faith, is a work, but 'tis Gods work.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 2.12.</note> 'Tis (expreſly) called a Faith of the Operation of God. As Faith is Gods will, ſo 'tis Gods work.</p>
               <p>'Tis a Faith that's wrought not only by the power of God,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> but by the exceeding greatneſs of Gods power. And what is
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:33854:62"/>the ſuper-eminent magnitude of his power to us-ward,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.19, 20.</note> who believe, according to the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the might of his power, which he wrought in Chriſt, when he raiſed him from the dead. There is concerned in the working of Faith, a power aequivalent unto, and aequipol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent with that power, which gave a Reſurrection to Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p>'Tis a Faith that hath a Train of good works.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam.</hi> 2 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Shew me thy Faith without thy works, and I will ſhew thee my Faith by my works</hi> By works, I mean, works from a right Principle, to right Ends; that is, works, from a gracious Principle, to a gracious end; works, from a Principle of the Grace of God, to a promotion of the Glory of God. Now, though ſuch works are not <hi>Eſſential</hi> unto Faith,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:33854:63"/>yet they are <hi>Evidential</hi> unto Faith; though, they are not the <hi>Eſſence</hi> of a lively Faith, yet, they are the <hi>Evidence</hi> that Faith lives;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.26.</note> 
                  <hi>For, as the Body, without the Spirit is dead; ſo Faith, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out works, is dead alſo.</hi> This, is a Goſpel-Faith, and he, or ſhe, that hath this Faith, is a Goſpel-Believer.</p>
               <p>What theſe promiſes are,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which Goſpel-Believers, have a Goſpel right. Promiſes (they ſay) are Abſolute, or Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional.</p>
               <p>Abſolute promiſes,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> are Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual,
<note place="margin">Abſolute.</note> and Caeleſtial; As Grace, and Glory; Redemption, and Remiſſion; Sanctification, and Salvation.</p>
               <p>Conditional promiſes,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> are temporal,
<note place="margin">Conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</note> and corporal; As Health, and Honour; Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and Plenty; Seed, and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:33854:63"/>But in ſhort, there's a three fold promiſe: Civil, Religious, and Divine.</p>
               <p>Civil.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> This is a word paſſed from Man, to Man.
<note place="margin">Civil.</note> A Civil promiſe, is a word paſſed from Man, to Man, for the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of ſome lawful thing, as in Contracts, and in other af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs. Thus, <hi>Laban,</hi> made pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to <hi>Jacob,</hi> to give him his Daughters. Thus, <hi>Saul,</hi> made promiſe to <hi>David,</hi> not to hurt him, and hunt his Soul, to take it. Thus (alſo) <hi>Jonathan,</hi> made promiſe to <hi>David,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.1, 2, 3.</p>
               <p>Religious.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> This is a word paſſed from Man, to God.
<note place="margin">Religious.</note> A religious promiſe, is a word paſſed from Man, to God, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſome Duty, relating to his Honour. This, is called a Vow. If a Woman (alſo) vow a vow unto the Lord. Thus,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:33854:64"/>the Pſalmiſt:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa</hi> 66.13, 14.</note> 
                  <hi>I will go into thy houſe with burnt-offerings, I will pay thee my vows, Which my lips have uttered, and my mouth hath ſpoken, when I was in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Divine.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> This, is a word paſſed from God to Man.
<note place="margin">Divine.</note> A di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine promiſe, is a word paſſed from God, to Man, concerning the fulfilling of ſome Good, or removing of ſome Evil, Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 119.38, 49, 50.</note> or Temporal. <hi>Stabliſh thy word unto thy Servant, who is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted to thy Fear. Remember thy word unto thy Servant, upon which thou haſt cauſed me to hope. This is my comfort in my affliction, for thy word hath quickened me</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, Gods promiſes, are Legal, or Evangelical.</p>
               <p>Legal.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                  <hi>Do this, and live.</hi> Thus God paſſed his word,
<note place="margin">Legal.</note> to give eternal life, and Creature-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, upon condition of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:33854:64"/>the Law. <hi>Honour thy Father, and thy Mother,</hi> which is the firſt Commandement with promiſe. But, theſe, are not the promiſes,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.2.</note> ſpoken off in the Text: <hi>To Abraham, and his Seed, were the promiſes made.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Evangelical. Thus,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> when God paſſeth his word freely to give;
<note place="margin">Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal.</note> freely to give Chriſt, and (to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with Chriſt) all things freely to give. Whereby are given unto us; but what? pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes; yea, precious promiſes, yea, great,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4.</note> and precious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes; yea, exceeding great, and precious promiſes. Now, theſe are they; they are Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>promiſes, unto which Goſpel-Believers, have a Goſpel-Right; Of theſe my Text ſpeak: <hi>To Abraham, and his Seed were the promiſes m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whether Goſpel-Believers,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> have a Goſpel Right, to Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>promiſes.
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:33854:65"/>It were no hard Task, to produce a cloud of witneſſes. But in the mouth of two, or three, ſhall every word be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.22.</note> For inſtance: <hi>The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath concluded all under ſin, that the promiſe by the Faith of Jeſus Chriſt might be given to them that believe.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.29.</note> If ye be Chriſts, then are ye Abrahams ſeed, and heirs, according to the promiſe. Now,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.28.</note> we, Brothren, as Iſaac was, are the Children of promiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How Goſpel-Believers,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> have a Goſpel-Right, to Goſpel-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</p>
               <p>Through Grace.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Free-Grace, gives a right to the promiſe.
<note place="margin">Through Grace.</note> Promiſes, are Donatives; they are free gifts.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.18.</note> 
                  <hi>If the Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance be of the Law, then 'tis no more by promiſe; but God gave it to Abraham by promiſe.</hi> Here, the Inheritance is given, that is under promiſe; and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:33854:65"/>is given, under which the inheritance is. God gave it to <hi>Abraeham</hi> by promiſe.</p>
               <p>Through Chriſt. Chriſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> is he firſt, and great Heir:
<note place="margin">Through Chriſt.</note> he is Heir of all things, and through <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im Believers inherit the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſe. 'Tis the Prince of life, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat gives a propriety in the promiſe of life. <hi>For this cauſe,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.15.</note> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e is the Mediatour of the New Teſtament, that by means of death, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or the Redemption of the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, that were under the firſt Teſtament, they which are called, might receive the promiſe of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. Inheritance.</hi> Here is an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal inheritance under promiſe, but this is through the death of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Through the Spirit.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Through the Spirit. Eph.</hi> 1.13.</note> is called the Spirit of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. <hi>After ye believed, ye were ſealed with that holy Spirit of promiſe.</hi> And, as there is the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:33854:66"/>Spirit of promiſe, ſo there the promiſe of the Spirit. The we might receive the promiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Spirit. 'Tis called th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> promiſe of the Spirit, not (o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) becauſe a greater efflux<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Spirit is under promiſe, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (alſo) becauſe the Spirit is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Author, and Applyer of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.</p>
               <p>Through Faith.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Faith,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Through Faith. Gal.</hi> 3.14.</note> is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Souls hand to receive the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. <hi>That the bleſſing of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham might come on the Gentile<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that we might receive the prom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of the Spirit;</hi> but how? <hi>throug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Faith.</hi> Here is Faith, but 't<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Faith from Chriſt; here is Faith but 'tis Faith in Chriſt; 't<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Faith that hath Chriſt for Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, as well as Author, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Actor; So that Grace, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt; the Spirit, and Faith i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt, give a Goſpel-Right, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Goſpel-promiſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:33854:66"/>Why Goſpel-Believers,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> have Goſpel-Right, to Goſpel-promiſes. The Reaſons follow. In order to the exerciſe of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elievers Faith.
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> As the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ept, is a <hi>Rule</hi> for <hi>Obedience,</hi> ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e promiſe, is a <hi>Ground</hi> for <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aith.</hi> The promiſes of God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad of the Goſpel, they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f I may ſpeak it without Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ity, and with a holy Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ence) the ſwadling Cloaths of Chriſt, and they carry a Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rapped up in them. Goſpel-promiſſes, they are full <hi>Breaſts,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd God delight that Faith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hould draw them.</p>
               <p>Oh Soul! when Time goes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto Eternity, then Faith will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o into <hi>Viſion;</hi> it muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be converſant about the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ruth of the promiſe here. 'Tis ſaid of <hi>Abraham,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.20, 21.</note> that <hi>he ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered not at the promiſe of God through unbelief, but was ſtrong
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:33854:67"/>in Faith, giving glory to God being fully perſwaded, that wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> God hath promiſed, he was ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> alſo to perform.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In order to the Exerciſe of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Believers Hope.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> As (Faith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> looks to the (Truth) of the pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, ſo (Hope) looks to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (Good) of the promiſe: A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Faith looks to the (Truth) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the promiſe. <hi>Ipſe dixit;</hi> 'T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> not <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> but God tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hath ſpoken it; <hi>And he is not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Man that he ſhould repent, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Son of Man that he ſhould ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> So Hope looks at the (Good) of the promiſe; at the <hi>Goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> couched, and lodged in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, whether it be a promiſe of the life that now is, or o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that which is to come. Abou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Good</hi> couched, and lodged in the promiſe, is Hope con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant; whether it be the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving of evil, or the obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:33854:67"/>of good.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 2 25.</note> 
                  <hi>This is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe which he hath promiſed us, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>even eternal life.</hi> Eternal life, is under promiſe, and this is the <hi>(Good)</hi> of the promiſe. But let the Apoſtle (who was a far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Orator then my ſelf) ſpeak, as to the <hi>Good,</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> of the promiſe. <hi>In hope of eternal life,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.2.</note> which God that cannot lye, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſed before the World began.</hi> In hope of Eternal life, there is the <hi>(Good)</hi> of the promiſe; <hi>which God that cannot lye, promiſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the World began.</hi> There's the <hi>(Truth)</hi> of the promiſe; Hope, is converſant about the one, and Faith is converſant about the other. Now, Goſpel-Believers, have a Goſpel-right, to Goſpel-promiſes, that Hope may be excerciſed; for, when <hi>Time</hi> goes into <hi>Eternity,</hi> then <hi>Hope</hi> will go into <hi>Poſſeſſion,</hi> as <hi>Faith</hi> will go into <hi>Viſion.</hi> Is it
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:33854:68"/>not proverbial, were it not for Hope, the heart would break? The Proverb (metaphyſically underſtood) is innocent; for, had Believers hope only in this life,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.19.</note> they were of all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures the moſt miſerable. Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-Believers, have ſomething in <hi>Hope,</hi> though nothing in <hi>Hand;</hi> much in the <hi>Promiſe,</hi> though little in the <hi>Purſe</hi> Hope (in ſome ſenſe) excels Faith; for <hi>the Devils believe,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.19.</note> and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble;</hi> yea, the Devils pray; They beſought Jeſus, to ſend them into the Deep. The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils believe,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 8.30.31.</note> and tremble, and pray: what want they then? they want Hope, which is a conſtant, and a confident ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of a promiſed good; this Devils can never have; they are under <hi>Torture,</hi> and <hi>Torment,</hi> and that without Hope of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.18.</note> A life of Hope, is
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:33854:68"/>the life of Believers; <hi>Abraham</hi> believed in Hope, againſt Hope. This Hope, Devils can never have, and do not this want here of make Devils?</p>
               <p>In order to a Believers <hi>Peace,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and <hi>Pardon,</hi> Goſpel-Believers, have a Goſpel-Right to Goſpel-promiſes, that in (them) they may read their Peace, and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. <hi>Now the God of Hope, fill you with Joy, and Peace;</hi> but how? through believing (<hi>Rom.</hi> 15.13.) That is, through believing the Peace, and the Pardon, laid up in the promiſe. The Goſpel, is a golden <hi>Mine</hi> of gracious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes; the leaſt promiſe (there) is worth a World, a thouſand Worlds, if there were ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.7.</note> 'Tis called the Goſpel of Chriſt. 'Tis called the Goſpel of God.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.1.</note> 'Tis called the Goſpel of Grace; and 'tis called the Goſpel of Peace.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 22.28</note> 
                  <hi>Your feet
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:33854:69"/>ſhod with the preparation of the Goſpel of Peace.</hi> The Goſpel, is Chriſts Letter of Credence, that when a poor drooping, doubting, and deſponding Sou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cannot ſee him, it may (in the promiſes thereof, and therein I read of him, and hear from him. The Wife is in <hi>Englaud,</hi> the Husband in <hi>India;</hi> oh how welcome is a Letter from him when ſhe cannot look upon him! Oh what a Lift to the Wife, is a Letter from the Husband under her poreing up on his Abſence, and Diſtance Oh ſay the Wife, though cannot look upon my Husband yet I have a Letter from m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Husband! And, though I can not ſee him, yet I hear from him, and read of him. 'Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thus here; to hear of a Chriſt, and hear from a Chriſt, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Believer cannot ſee him
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:33854:69"/>is a Believers Mercy, and this is the promiſes of the Goſpel. Now, Goſpel-Believers, have a Goſpel-Right, to Goſpel-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, in order to their Peace, and Pardon. <hi>Whom,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8.</note> having not ſeen, ye love, in whom, though now ye ſee him not, yet believing, ye rejoice with joy unſpeakable, and full of Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In order to a Believers ſtrength, and ſupport.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Goſpel-Believers, have a Goſpel-right, to Goſpel-promiſes, that (in the promiſes) they may read a promiſed Strength, and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port. Oh, ſay the Soul, that Scripture ring in my ears, and follow me whither ſoever I go! <hi>It ſhall come to paſs,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 19 17.</note> that him which eſcapeth the ſword of</hi> Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zael, <hi>ſhall</hi> Jehu <hi>ſlay; and him that eſcapeth the ſword of</hi> Jehu, <hi>ſhall</hi> Eliſha <hi>ſlay.</hi> Oh, ſay the Soul, if I do not fall by the
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:33854:70"/>hands of this <hi>Saul,</hi> I may by the hands of that <hi>Achan!</hi> If I do not fall by the hands of this <hi>Achan,</hi> I may by the hands of that <hi>Goliah!</hi> Oh! If I do not fall by the hands of this Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I may fall by the hands of that Temptation; And, if I fall not by the hands of that Temptation, I may fall by the hands of this Corruption. But, Soul, art a Goſpel-Believer? then thou haſt a Goſpel-Right, to Goſpel-promiſes, that (in the promiſes) thou mayſt read a promiſed Strength, and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port under Temptation, under Corruption. God (by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet) ſpeaking of <hi>Abraham</hi> his Friend, and his Seed, makes, and leaves a precious promiſe: <hi>Fear thou not;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.8.10.</note> why? <hi>for I am with thee:</hi> be not diſmaid; why? <hi>for I am thy God;</hi> but what then? I will ſtrengthen Thee; yea, I
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:33854:70"/>will help Thee; yea, I will up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold Thee, by the right hand of my righteouſneſs. Here, ye may read (under promiſe) the preſence, and the power of God; Strength, and Support from God; Now, <hi>to Abraham, and his Seed, were the promiſes made.</hi> Oh, ſay the Soul, I am weak! weak as water! ſaith God, I will ſtrengthen. Oh, ſay the Soul, the work is too hard for me! and too much for me! ſaith God, I will help. Oh, ſay the Soul, I may flay by the way! fail by the way! fall by way! No, ſaith God, I will up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thee, ane that by the right hand of my righteouſneſs.</p>
               <p>What uſe may be made of this, that Goſpel-Believers,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> have a Goſpel-Right, to Goſpel-promiſes.</p>
               <p>Theſe are three Uſes: Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror; Trial; Triumph.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:33854:71"/>Art an Unbeliever?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> tremble (then) for thou (haſt at preſent) no Goſpel;
<note place="margin">By way of Terror.</note> Right, to Goſpel-promiſes. Oh Soul! thou canſt never look upon the (promiſe) of life as thine, until thou canſt look upon (Prince) of life as thine. Providential Mercies, fall upon all Creatures, but the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of Mercies, and Mercies in the promiſes, are ſetled up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Spouſe as her proper, and peculiar Dowry. If, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to haſt no Goſpel-proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the Prince, and Saviour; thou haſt no Goſpel-propriety, to the promiſe of Life, and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. Art in a ſtate of Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief? Oh how may trembling (then) take hold upon thee, for thou haſt no Goſpel-right, to any Goſpel-promiſe. Whether thou haſt a decretive right, I know not, but a declarative right thou haſt not, for, <hi>to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:33854:71"/>and his Seed, were the promiſes made</hi> Is not that a ſad word? <hi>At that time,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12.</note> ye were without Chriſt;</hi> without Chriſt! what then? Soul, is it nothing to be without Chriſt? To be without the Prince of Life, is to be without the promiſe of life: Chriſt is the firſt, and grand promiſe, <hi>the ſeed of the woman;</hi> all after promiſes, are but as ſo many Comments upon this firſt, and grand promiſe, Chriſt. Is it nothing (then) to be without Chriſt? But what follows? <hi>Being aliens of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth of Iſrael, and Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers from the Covenants of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, having no hope, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God in the World.</hi> Did <hi>Spira</hi> ſay (when his Friends were reading of comfortable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, about the death of Chriſt) <q>read no more; read no more; read no more; they are Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dials
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:33854:72"/>to others,</q> they are Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſives to me. Oh what mayſt thou then ſay, that art in a ſtate of unbelief! I would have more Charity for him, then for thee, if thou beeſt an Unbeliever, for, <hi>to Abraham, and his Seed, were the promiſes made.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Have Goſpel-Believers,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> a Goſpel-Right,
<note place="margin">By way of T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ial.</note> to Goſpel-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes? Try (then) whether thou haſt a Goſpel-right.</p>
               <p>The Queſtions (now) will be theſe.</p>
               <p>But how ſhall I know,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtio </seg>1</label> that I have a Goſpel-Right, to Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-promiſes?</p>
               <p>Haſt Chriſt?
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Solut. </seg>
                  </label> then thou haſt a Goſpel-right, to Goſpel-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes. If Chriſt be thine, all is thine. What one ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity:
<note place="margin">Chriſtus meus, &amp; omnia.</note> 
                  <hi>Antiqua mea, Chriſtus meus:</hi> my Antiquity, is my Chriſt; I may ſay of propriety, <hi>proprietas mea, Chriſtus meus;</hi>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:33854:72"/>propriety is my Chriſt.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32.</note> He that ſpared not his own Son, but delivered him up for us all, how ſhall he not with him (alſo) freely give unto us all things?</p>
               <p>But how ſhall I know that Chriſt is mine?
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>2</label>
               </p>
               <p>Haſt the Spirit?
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution. </seg>
                  </label> then thou haſt Chriſt.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 3.24.</note> 
                  <hi>By this we know that he abideth in us, by the Spirit which he hath given us.</hi> This is an infallible Evidence.</p>
               <p>But how ſhall I know that I have the Spirit?
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>3</label>
               </p>
               <p>Haſt the Fruits of the Spirit?
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Solut. </seg>
                  </label> then thou haſt the Spirit. Though there may be a Tree without Fruit, yet there can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be Fruit without a Tree: Now, the Spirit, is not a barren, but a bearing Tree; it bears Variety, and Rarity; it bears Variety; as Love, Joy, Peace, long-ſuffering, gentleneſs,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22, 23.</note> good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Faith, Meekneſs, Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance;
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:33854:73"/>it (alſo) bears Rarity, Faith, Love, &amp;c. ſuch Fruit as this.</p>
               <p>I will take but one of the Top-fruits of this Tree, and that's Faith. Haſt Faith? a Faith, that hath Chriſt, for Object? Chriſt, for Author? Chriſt for Actor? then thou haſt the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and a Goſpel-Right, to Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-promiſes. <hi>To Abraham, and his Seed, were the promiſes made. He that believeth on the Son of God,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Jo</hi> 5 10.</note> hath the witneſs in himſelf.</hi> Where this Faith is, there is the Spirit; he that hath the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, hath Chriſt; and he that hath Chriſt, hath a Goſpel-Right, to Goſpel-promiſes.</p>
               <p>But how ſhall I know when a promiſe is given from God?
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>4</label> Oh I fear, I take promiſes, before they are given of God!</p>
               <p>Then a promiſe is given of God,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>lut.</hi> 1.</note> when it comes not in
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:33854:73"/>word onely. A promiſe, from God, comes in word,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſ</hi> 1.5</note> 
                  <hi>but not in word onely, but in power, and in the hely Spirit.</hi> Our Goſpel, came not to you in word only, but alſo in power, and in the holy Spirit, and in much aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. A promiſe come in word; there muſt be a word; yea, this the written word; or, (at leaſt) ſomething aequivalent unto the written Word; yet it comes not in words only, but alſo in power.</p>
               <p>Then a promiſe comes from God, when the Soul is enabled,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and influenced, to receive it. That we might receive the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the Spirit. Now, this receiving is believing, for Faith is the Souls hand.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 1.12.</note> 
                  <hi>To as many us received him, to them gave he power</hi> (or priviledge) <hi>to become the Sons of God;</hi> but who are theſe? Even to as many as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:33854:74"/>to his Name. For the Soul to ſay, this is the word of God, and (through Grace) I believe it; when the Soul can ſay, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning a promiſe, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid concerning the ſafety of the Souls, under the loſs of the Ship, I believe God, that it ſhall be as it was told me; So, when the Soul can believe the promiſe; this promiſe is mine, &amp;c. then 'tis given from God.</p>
               <p>Then a promiſe is given from God,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> when 'tis engraven upon the heart. 'Tis true, Satan can produce Scriptures, and preſent promiſes, but when promiſes are written upon the heart, then they come from God. When the Soul keep a freſh ſenſe of the promiſe upon the heart, and can ſay with the Pſalmiſt: <hi>I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the dayes of old,</hi> it looks (then) as if it were given from God.
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.2, 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Ye are our Epiſtle written
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:33854:74"/>in our hearts, known, and read read of all Men; For as much as ye are manifeſtly declared to be the Epiſtle of Chriſt, miniſtred by us, written not with Ink, but with the Spirit of the living God, not in tables of ſtone, but in fleſhly tables of the heart.</hi> Are there not ſome of you here, that remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the very firſt promiſe, wherein Chriſt, and your Souls met? and you cannot forget that, and other promiſes, alſo.</p>
               <p>Then a promiſe is given from God,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> when it ſutes the Souls condition. For inſtance,</p>
               <p>Art tempted? Oh,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ſay the Soul, my Temptations are wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, and wicked! horrid, and ſordid! brutiſh, and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous! <hi>Bleſſed, is the Man,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.12.</note> that endureth Temptation, for when he is tryed, he ſhall receive the Crown of life, which God hath promiſed to them that love him.</hi>
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:33854:75"/>Now, this ſuit is the Souls con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
               <p>Art afflicted?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Oh, ſay the Soul, I can look no way, but I may ſay, <hi>Gad,</hi> a Troop com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth! My afflictions come like waves, no ſooner is one affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction over, but another com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.9.</note> 
                  <hi>In all their affliction, he was afflicted.</hi> He was affected, with their affliction, and they had his Affection, under their Affliction. This word ſutes the preſent Condition.</p>
               <p>Art perſecuted?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Oh, ſay the Soul,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Saul hunts after my Soul to take it!</hi> Perſecuted, but not forſaken. Though perſecuted of Man, yet not forſaken by God. This falls in with the Souls condition, and ſo looks like a word given from God.</p>
               <p>Art diſſerted?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Oh, ſay the Soul, the Sun of Righteouſneſs is gone down upon me, and
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:33854:75"/>there's a Cloud interpoſing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween my Soul, and my Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our!
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.7.</note> 
                  <hi>For a ſmall moment have I forſaken thee, but with great mercies will I gather thee.</hi> Doth not this ſute the Condition of the Soul?</p>
               <p>Art reproached? Oh,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> ſay the Soul, they lay to my charge things that I know not!
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed are ye, when men ſhall revile you, and ſpeak all manner of evil a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you</hi> (falſly) <hi>for my ſake.</hi> Is not this word ſutable?</p>
               <p>Art impoveriſhed? Oh,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> ſay the Soul, my Barrel is empty! and my Cruſe empty!
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 34.10.</note> 
                  <hi>The young Lyons do lack, and ſuffer hunger, but they that ſeek the Lord, ſhall not want any good thing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They ſhall not want any thing that is good, that is for their good. Is not this promiſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and ſeaſonale?</p>
               <p>Art Unbelieving? Oh,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> ſay
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:33854:76"/>the Soul, my Faith is at a low Ebb, and I cannot make con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of Light in Darkneſs, of Life in Death, which is the true Logick of Faith?
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim</hi> 2.12.</note> 
                  <hi>If we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve not, yet he abideth faithful, he cannot deny himſelf.</hi> If not this a ſutable word?</p>
               <p>Art mourning?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Oh, ſay the Soul, mine Eye is like a Lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beck, continually dropping! <hi>I,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.12.</note> even I am he that comforteth thee.</hi> Not I, and another; not I, or another; but I, <hi>even I am he that comforteth thee.</hi> This falls in with the preſent ſtate.</p>
               <p>Doſt want Pardon?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Oh, ſay the Soul, I want a ſight, and a Senſe of Pardon! There's no Salvation, without Remiſſion, and yet I want a Sight, and a Senſe of that.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.25.</note> 
                  <hi>I, even I am he that blotteth out thy Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions for mine own ſake, and will not remember thy Sins.</hi> Is not this proper?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:33854:76"/>Haſt back-ſliden? Oh,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> ſay the Soul, I have a ſliding foot, and a back-ſliding Heart!
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 15.4.</note> 
                  <hi>I will heal their back-ſliding, I will love them freely.</hi> Is not this a proper promiſe?</p>
               <p>Doſt fear? Oh, ſay the Soul,
<note place="margin">Laſtly.</note> I fear I ſhall fall by the ſtrength of this Temptation! or this Corruption!
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9.</note> 
                  <hi>My Grace is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for Thee, for my power is made perfect in weakneſs.</hi> A promiſe (thus coming) ſutes the Souls condition, and ſeems (to me) to be a promiſe given from God.</p>
               <p>Art a Believer?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Triumph (then) thy Salvation is under Promiſe. Soul,
<note place="margin">By way of Triumph.</note> though Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be a great thing; though it be a Soul-Salvation; a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Salvation; an eternal Salvation, yet, this Salvation is under promiſe, and is entail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon believing.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Receiving
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:33854:77"/>the End of your Faith, the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of your Souls.</hi> As Faith ſhall have an End, ſo there is the end of Faith, and that's Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; <hi>receiving the end of your Faith, even the Salvation of your Souls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There muſt be believing, till Faith come to an end, if (at the End) you would receive the End of your Faith, even the Salvation of your Souls. When Faith ſhall have an End, then ſhall the Soul have the End of Faith, and that's Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; Receiving the end of your Faith, even the Salvation of your Souls. Soul, take a Drop into thy Bucket; pluck a Cluſter from this Vine, Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-Promiſes, they are (as it were) the Veins of Chriſt, whereby his Bloud is carried in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all his body, the Church. Goſpel-promiſes, they are the
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:33854:77"/>Treaſures of Comforts; they are the Churches Stock; they are the Believers Patrimony; <hi>To Abraham, and his Seed, were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Promiſes made.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.17.</note> It is the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge and Dignity of true Believers, to be called heirs of the Promiſe.</p>
               <p>Oh,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion. </seg>
                  </label> but a Cloud ſeems to be impending! Is not Sin reeling ſtill? Is not Satan raging ſtill? What courſe ſhall I now ſteer, for the bitterneſs of Death is not yet paſt?
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution. </seg>
                  </label>
               </p>
               <p>Make Judgment of Gods Faithfulneſs, not according to his <hi>Providences,</hi> but according to his <hi>Promiſes.</hi> God, hath promiſed to keep his People, and he will keep his Promiſe. Providences, may work coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but Promiſes are the ſame, and are ſure. Whatever is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, the promiſe is ſure. An Eſtate may be loſt; Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:33854:78"/>may dye, and go to the Grave of Silence, but the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is ſure, and the ſame <hi>Therefore it is of Faith,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.16.</note> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> might be by Grace;</hi> why? <hi>to the end the promiſe might be ſure t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> all the Seed.</hi> To all the Seed but what Seed is this? <hi>not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> that (onely) which is of the Law but to that (alſo) which is of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Faith of Abraham, who is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Father of us all.</hi> Now, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Soul may be filled (like th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> water pots of <hi>Galilee</hi>) up t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the very Brim, with Joy, and Peace, through believing, ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer me to tell thee, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> promiſes are ſure, and the ſame For</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> They are hid in the Scripture <hi>That the Gentiles ſhould be fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low heirs,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.6.</note> and of the ſame body and partakers of his promiſe;</hi> but how? through the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> They are hid in the Heart
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:33854:78"/>
                  <hi>With the heart man believeth unto Righteouſueſs,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.12.</note> and with the mouth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>onfeſſion is made unto Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They are hid in Chriſt.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
                  <hi>All <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e Promiſes of God,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20</note> in Him</hi> that is, in Chriſt) <hi>are YEA, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd in him AMEN, unto the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lory of God by us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, to end, as I did begin; Divine Promiſes, they are hid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the Scripture; but ſhould that be made a Sacrifice, then they are hid in the Heart: Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-Promiſes, they are hid in the Heart; but ſhould that be made a Sacrifice, then they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id in Chriſt, and are they not ſure enough there? Oh, Soul! <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> am ſure, there they are ſure. Now, Goſpel-Believers, have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Goſpel-Right, to Goſpel-Promiſes. Art a Believer of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he right Stamp? theſe Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes (then) are thine, and wilt
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:33854:79"/>thou go away with a Count<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance ſad? Oh Soul! ope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thy mouth wide, that it ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be filled with Grace, and Peace For, <hi>To</hi> Abraham, <hi>and his Sec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> were the Promiſes made.</hi>
               </p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 2.14</bibl>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:33854:79"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <list>
               <head>Books to be Sold by <hi>Beniamin Harris,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Stationers Arms,</hi> in <hi>Swithins</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, in <hi>Corn-hill,</hi> near the Royal Exchange.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>WAr with the Devil,</hi> or, The Young Mans Conflict with the Powers of Darkneſs. By <hi>B. K.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> Bound, is.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Parable of the Kingdom of Heaven:</hi> Or, An Expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the firſt 13 <hi>ver.</hi> of the 25th. Chap. of St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> By Mr. <hi>Knowllis,</hi> 8. <hi>Price</hi> bound 1 s.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Loving, and Waſhing;</hi> Or ſome Meditations upon Loving, &amp; Waſhing in the Blood of Chriſt, by <hi>Richard Mayhew; Price</hi> bound 10. d.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:33854:80"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33854:80"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
